这里还有这
And here we are
从银针落地的细微声
From the gentle sound of a silver needle falling
到飞机引擎的震耳轰鸣
To the deafening roar of a jet engine
现在，放松自己
Now, relax
让我们享受一段精彩的电影之旅
And let's embark on an amazing movie journey
天地灵气孕育出一颗混元珠
The essence of heaven and earth gave birth to a Mystic Pearl
元始天尊将其一分为二
The Primordial Deity split it into two
仙气化作灵珠
The divine essence became the Spirit Pearl
魔气聚为魔丸
The malevolent essence formed the Demon Pearl
且在魔丸上施下
And on the Demon Pearl, he cast
天劫咒
The Heaven's Wrath Curse
三年后引天雷摧毁魔丸
To summon a celestial thunderbolt to destroy the Demon Pearl in three years
后有申公豹从中作梗
But Shen Gongbao interfered
魔丸投胎为陈塘关三太子哪吒
The Demon Pearl was reincarnated as Nezha, the Third Prince of Chen Tang Pass
而灵珠则投胎为龙王三太子敖丙
While the Spirit Pearl was reborn as Ao Bing, the Third Prince of the Dragon King
机缘巧合下
By a twist of fate
二人居然结为挚友
The two became close friends
魔丸哪吒受父母感化
Nezha, the Demon Pearl, was moved by his parents' love
褪去魔性
And shed his demonic nature
拯救了陈塘关
Saving Chen Tang Pass
并与傲骨携手共抗天劫
And joining forces with Ao Bing to face the celestial thunder
最终扭转了命运
Ultimately changing their fates
虽扛下了天劫
Though you withstood the celestial thunder
但你们的肉身被毁
Your physical bodies were destroyed
魂魄若无依托，片刻便会魂飞魄散
Your spirits will dissipate in moments without a vessel
七岁宝莲主要守护及孕育
The Seven-Year-Old Sacred Lotus is here to protect and nurture
为师现在就要用它为你们重塑肉身
I will now use it to recreate your physical forms
哇~！开工！
Wow! Let's get started!
画风不对啊
Something's not right here.
没错啊，仙藕制作成藕粉
That's correct, the lotus root needs to be ground into powder.
才能重塑肉身啊
Only then can it reshape the body.
你刚才是不是用抠了脚的手在做藕粉
Did you just use your foot-scratching hand to make the powder?
哦
Oh.
没事儿，脚上沾一些
It's fine, a little from the feet won't hurt.
一会儿洗洗脚就好了
We can wash your feet later.
我不是关心你的脚
I'm not worried about your feet.
嗯，你刚才是不是在擤鼻涕?
Yeah, were you just blowing your nose?
哎呀，没鼻涕没鼻涕
Oh no, no snot, no snot
这是藕粉，看到了吗?
This is lotus root powder, see?
藕粉啊
Lotus root powder
藕粉拌好了啊
The lotus root powder is mixed
来来来来来
Come on, come on, come on
你们一人一坨💩
Each of you gets a blob💩
呃，不是，额，一份
Uh, no, I mean, one portion
搞快点，你的魂都要散咯
Hurry up, your spirit is about to scatter
让我散了得了
Let me scatter, then
臭讲究凑，你花样儿挺多哟
Such fuss, you sure have a lot of tricks
哈哈，能动了耶
Ha, I can move!
嗯
Hmm
这啥玩意儿？哎，谢谢啊
What's this? Oh, thank you
我就说刚才怎么找不见了呢
I was wondering where it went
呵呵嘿嘿嘿
Hehehehe
飞天猪的记忆力无人能及
Flying Pig's memory is unmatched
雕刻技术也是巧夺天工
His carving skills are also masterful
你瞅一下像不像？啊！啊！啊！
Does it look like it? Ah! Ah! Ah!
多谢猪兄啊，不要动
Thanks, Pig Brother, don't move
你的身体还没有定型
Your body hasn't set yet
仙长，我已召集陈塘关全军戒备
Immortal, I have gathered all the troops of Chen Tang Pass on alert
以防申公豹和东海龙族来犯
To prevent Shen Gongbao and the East Sea Dragon Clan from attacking
放心，龙族都在镇压海底妖兽
Don't worry, the Dragon Clan is suppressing the sea monsters
我担保他们一条都出不来
I guarantee not one will come out
一个申公豹就没啥子好怕的
One Shen Gongbao isn't much to fear
嘿嘿，你们还是来看一下
Hehe, you should still take a look
像不像啊?
Does it look like it?
我教的手艺
The skills I taught
不过也没必要一模一样嘛
But it doesn't have to be exactly the same
可以再美化些吗
Can it be more beautiful?
啊
Ah
嗯，也对
Hmm, that's true
哪个父母不想儿子变得更优秀呢
Which parent doesn't want their son to be better?
改的高大威猛些
Make it taller and more robust
还要俊美秀气
And more handsome and delicate
男子汉就得阳刚硬朗
A man should be strong and rugged
相貌英俊帅气
Handsome and dashing
还要可爱乖巧
And cute and sweet
到底怎么改你们统一下意见
Figure out what you want, already
高大威猛
Tall and strong
兼备俊美秀气
With a touch of elegance
阳刚硬朗
Rugged and tough
不失活泼可爱
Yet playful and adorable
啥意思啊
What do you mean?
他的意思是你行你上，哼
He means if you can do better, go ahead, hmph
早该我来了
It's about time I stepped in
自己做的才最满意嘛
You do your best work yourself, of course
哼，这下有得等了
Humph, this is going to take a while
先给你定型吧，啊
Let's start with your shape, okay?
你天生水象，需以坎水淬炼
You're naturally water-like, so we'll temper you with water
打开
Open up
啊~大功告成。你做好了吗？
Ah~ All done. Are you ready?
差不多吧
Pretty much
哼
Humph
虽然这版肯定是最出彩的
This version is definitely the standout
但是细节打磨还需要很长时间
But it needs a lot more refining
不如暂时就用第一版的吧
How about we use the first version for now?
对，第一版还是可以的
Yeah, the first version is fine
嗯，我也觉得
Mm-hmm, I agree
嗯嗯
Mm-hmm
天生火象需以离火煅烧
You're naturally fire-like, so we'll forge you with fire
海面出现敌情
Enemy spotted at sea
好像是申公豹
It looks like Shen Gongbao.
有多少敌人？就他一人。诶
How many enemies? Just him. Huh.
奇怪
Strange.
您继续施法
Please continue your spell.
我等前去御敌
We will go and face the enemy.
仙长，让我去跟师父求求情
Elder, let me go plead with Master.
你不要动，你还需要一炷香的时间
Don't move, you still need a moment.
然后你的身体才能稳定
Then your body will stabilize.
申公豹，你去而复返是何用意
Shen Gongbao, what brings you back?
你们既已知晓
Since you already know,
我和龙族的计划
about my plan with the Dragon Clan,
我心里始终不肯踏实
I can't help but feel uneasy.
陈塘关现有重兵把守
Chentang Pass is heavily guarded.
太乙仙长也在城内
Elder Taiyi is also in the city.
你单枪匹马
You're going in alone,
我觉得你难有什么作为
I doubt you'll accomplish much.
谁....谁说我单枪匹马
Who said I'm going in alone?
盗取灵珠之事一旦败露出来
If the theft of the Spirit Pearl is exposed,
别说替你的儿子报仇
forget about avenging your son.
就算你是东海龙族
Even as a Dragon Clan of the East Sea,
你也罪责难逃
you won't escape punishment.
等事情败露
Once the truth comes out,
你也被打入海底炼狱
you'll be sent to the Underwater Hell.
下面那里全是你的老熟人
You'll meet all your old friends down there.
看我们怎么招待你
We'll see how we treat you.
出不了龙宫
You won't leave the Dragon Palace.
报不你儿子的血海深仇
You won't avenge your son's deep grudge.
我都替你着急
I'm worried for you.
哈哈哈哈哈哈哈哈
Hahahahahaha.
还轮不到你们在这幸灾乐祸
It's not your turn to gloat.
小妹我想献计
Little sister has a plan to offer.
看来大哥是不领情了
It seems Big Brother isn't grateful.
大哥怕是忘了小妹的能耐
Big Brother must have forgotten Little Sister's skills.
我知道，裂...裂..裂空爪
I know, the... the... Sky-Splitting Claw!
谢谢
Thanks.
若申道长携带这个龙爪
If Daoist Master Ruo Shen carries this Dragon Claw
前去陈塘关
to Chentang Pass,
切开直通本王身边的裂缝
it will create a rift leading straight to my side.
海底妖族便帮助大哥铲平陈塘关
The sea demons will help Big Brother level Chentang Pass.
海底妖族
The sea demons?
这怎么可能
How is that possible?
1000年前镇压在锁妖坠下的妖族能出得来？
Can the demons sealed under the Demon Lock for a thousand years really escape?
龙..龙族已经把他们放了吗？
Has the Dragon Clan really set them free?
有定海锁链相连
With the Sea-Stabilizing Chains still in place,
也不必担心我们逃的掉
there's no need to worry about us escaping.
这两全其美的借兵之法
This is a perfect plan to borrow an army.
大哥满意吗？
Are you satisfied, Big Brother?
你会这么好心吗？
Are you being this nice?
说吧
Speak up.
你的条件。啊哈哈
Your terms. Hahaha.
这炼狱里呀
In this hellish place,
烈焰焚身，度日如年
flames burn the body, and days feel like years.
若大哥稍微降低岩浆火力
If Big Brother could just slightly reduce the lava's heat,
缓解灼烧之苦
to ease our burning pain,
我等甘效犬马之劳
we will serve you loyally.
申公豹在搞什么名堂
What is Shen Gongbao up to?
终于出来了！耶
Finally out! Yeah!
拜拜~！呜呼呼呼哈哈哈哈
Bye-bye~! Hahaha!
卑鄙呀
How despicable!
完了，这下怎么向李大人交代啊
Oh no, how can we explain this to Lord Li?
还好没有人看到
Luckily, no one saw.
给。干嘛？
Here. What for?
我把你打残
I'll cripple you.
你把我打残
You cripple me.
就说是夜叉干的
Just say it was the demon.
哦，李大人看我们被打得那么惨
Oh, Lord Li will see us beaten so badly.
就不会怪罪我们了
He won't blame us then.
别手软啊
Don't hold back.
使点劲
Put some effort into it.
哎哎，嗯嗯。喂？你们两个
Hey hey, hmm hmm. Hey? You two.
仙长，您怎么在这儿呢？
Immortal, what are you doing here?
嘿嘿嘿~~哈哈哈
Hehehe~~ Hahaha
夜叉是他放走的
The demon was set free by him.
嗯？啊？你放屁！
Huh? What? You're talking nonsense!
明明是你粗心大意
Clearly, it's your carelessness.
你含血喷人
You're spouting lies.
你推卸责任啊
You're just trying to shift the blame.
呜呜呜啊啊~哎？
Waaaaah~ Hmm?
两个神经病
Two nutcases.
喂
Hey
你们两个别打了。你们俩给我滚过来
Stop fighting, both of you. Get over here.
给我护法
Protect me.
是，是，是，好的，好的，好的
Yes, yes, yes, okay, okay, okay.
不留活口
No survivors.
申公豹,敖丙并未殒命
Shen Gongbao, Ao Bing did not die.
陈塘关和龙族并非势不两立
Chen Tang Pass and the Dragon Clan are not sworn enemies.
太乙仙长正在为敖丙重塑肉身
Immortal Taiyi is restoring Ao Bing's body.
信口雌黄
What a load of rubbish.
结界？
Barrier?
师父，师父！熬丙。太乙师伯为徒儿重塑了肉身
Master, Master! Ao Bing. Uncle Taiyi has restored my body.
快快停战吧
Stop the fighting, quick!
诶诶诶，申公豹
Hey, Shen Gongbao.
我救了你徒弟
I saved your disciple.
你该怎么感谢我？
How do I thank you?
那这里边就是哪吒喽
So this is Nezha.
嗨呀，你个没良心的
Hey, you ungrateful thing!
师傅，他们必须死
Master, they must die.
哼，哼，哈哈哈
Humph, humph, ha ha ha.
就凭你破得了这结界
You think you can break this barrier?
你打我噻
Come on, hit me!
你打我噻，哈哈哈
Come on, hit me! Ha ha ha!
不要这么做
Don't do it.
这气息
This aura...
熬丙。父王。
Ao Bing. Father.
父王
Father.
孩儿未能完成
I couldn't complete it.
孩儿未能完成龙族的事。不
I couldn't complete the dragon clan's mission. No.
那些事情不再重要
Those things don't matter anymore.
我只要你活着
I just want you alive.
活着，活着就好
Alive, that's all that matters.
啊，你的身体怎么了？哎呀
Ah, what's wrong with your body? Oh no!
刚制作的肉身，怎么能遭得住这么强的冲击！
A newly crafted body can't withstand such a strong impact!
熬丙
Ao Bing
喂，你的身体还没固定完成，你不要动，不要动
Hey, your body isn't fully formed yet. Don't move, don't move!
熬丙，你怎么了？
Ao Bing, what's wrong with you?
你的肉身还没定型
Your physical form isn't stable yet.
你为什么要这样?
Why are you doing this?
以后你的身体超过负荷的话也会崩的呀
If you push yourself too hard, your body will fall apart.
哎呀呀，你怎么能这样。死胖子
Oh no, how could you do this? fatty
还不赶紧给敖丙做...做个肉身
Hurry up and make... make a physical form for Ao Bing.
嗯？
Huh?
连续制作两个肉身
Creating two physical forms in a row
宝莲的仙气都耗光了
has drained all of Bao Lian's divine energy.
没有肉身不是会魂飞魄散吗？
Without a physical form, won't you lose your soul?
师父，你想想办法啊
Master, please think of something!
没有宝莲仙气，我，我也没有办法
Without Bao Lian's divine energy, I... I can't do anything.
没关系
It's okay.
是我占了灵珠才连累了你
It's because I took the Spirit Pearl that you're in trouble.
若以我一命
If my life
能换你重生也算稍微减轻我的罪恶感
can give you a chance to be reborn, it might ease my guilt a bit.
谁让你顶罪
Why should you take the blame?
当魔丸我也一样活的开心
I can live happily as a Demon Pearl too.
我不准你死
I won't let you die.
求你放过陈塘关吧
Please spare Chen Tang Pass.
我们不能一错再错
We can't keep making the same mistakes.
这是孩儿最后的心愿
This is my final wish.
你肯定还有办法
You must have another way.
你必须要有办法
You've got to figure something out.
快点想办法，快
Hurry up and think of something, quick!
让敖丙先借用你的身体
Let Ao Bing borrow your body first.
借用你的身体
Borrow your body.
两个魂魄共用一个肉身
Two souls sharing one body
必会相互排斥
will inevitably repel each other.
灵珠，魔丸本自同根生
The Spirit Pearl and the Demon Pill were born from the same root.
共用一个肉身
Sharing one body.
七天内没得问题呀
It should be fine for seven days.
好啊，熬丙，你快下来，快
Alright, Ao Bing, come down, quick!
好
Okay.
好奇怪的感觉
What a strange feeling.
熬丙，你在吗
Ao Bing, are you there?
哦，我在我脑袋里能听到你的声音
Oh, I'm here. I can hear your voice in my head.
哎呀，好玩！好玩！真好玩
Wow, this is fun! Fun! So much fun!
这也只是权宜之计
This is just a temporary solution.
七天后又当如何
What about after seven days?
玉虚宫的宝库里有种法宝
There's a treasure in the Jade Void Palace.
名叫玉液琼浆
It's called the Jade Liquid Elixir.
有恢复法器神力的功效
It has the power to restore the divine strength of magical artifacts.
用它浇灌后
After using it to water the plant,
七色宝莲一定会重新开花
the Seven-Colored Treasure Lotus will bloom again.
那你想如何取过来呢
So, how do you plan to get it?
当然是求天尊赏赐啊
Of course, we'll ask the Celestial Master for a gift.
哼，难不成你要告发我和龙族
Humph, or are you going to report me and the Dragon Clan?
天尊又岂会救..救龙族之子
Would the Celestial Master ever save... save the son of the Dragon Clan?
求不到
If we can't ask,
那就抢
then we'll take it by force.
玉虚宫乃阐教核心，高手如云
The Jade Void Palace is the heart of the Exoteric School, filled with experts.
为了我儿就是天庭
For my son, even the Heavenly Court
我也不在乎
I wouldn't care.
龙王请稍安勿躁
Dragon King, please calm down.
我倒有一计
I have a plan.
禅教弟子、修行道家皆可参加升仙考核
Disciples of Zen and Taoist practitioners can all participate in the Immortal Ascension Exam.
通过考核不仅可得道成仙
Passing the test not only grants immortality,
还能在玉虚宝库任选一样法宝作为奖励
but also allows you to choose a magical treasure from the Jade Treasure House.
你是说让哪吒参加考核
You mean having Nezha take the test?
取得玉液琼浆
To obtain the Jade Elixir.
哎呀，要不得，要不得呀
Oh no, that's not a good idea.
他浑身魔气
He's brimming with demonic energy.
只要他功夫身份就暴露了
He'll expose himself the moment he uses his powers.
敖丙不是依附哪吒身上了吗
Isn't Ao Bing already attached to Nezha?
正好用灵气掩盖魔气
His spiritual energy can cover up the demonic aura.
只要七天内通过考核
As long as he passes the test within seven days,
不仅可以取得玉液琼琼奖
Not only can he obtain the Jade Elixir,
还可以...还可以成仙
but he can also... become immortal.
我成仙了以后，我是不是不算魔啦
If I become immortal, will I no longer be considered a demon?
既救敖丙也救哪吒
This way, we save both Ao Bing and Nezha.
皆皆大欢喜
Everyone wins.
此举绝非正道
This is not the righteous path.
哼，那你说怎么办？按规矩办事
Humph, what do you suggest? Follow the rules?
禀明天尊
Report to the Heavenly Lord.
盼天尊明察秋毫
May the Heavenly Lord see the truth.
我夫妇俩也会竭力相求
My wife and I will do our utmost to plead.
不让父辈之罪祸及两个无辜孩儿
To prevent the sins of the past from harming these two innocent children.
区区凡人，几十年的阅历
You, a mere mortal with a few decades of experience,
就敢在我面前讲大道理
dare to lecture me on righteousness?
呃，呃，
Uh, uh,
我已经记不清楚了活了几千年了
I've lost count of the thousands of years I've lived.
我老人家只告诉你一个道理
Let me impart a bit of wisdom to you.
我儿若死了
If my son dies,
全陈塘关的人都得陪葬
everyone in Chen Tang Pass will pay with their lives.
啊啊啊！住手
Ah! Stop!
熬丙是我朋友
Ao Bing is my friend.
我肯定会救他
I will definitely save him.
但你要敢动陈塘关
But if you dare touch Chen Tang Pass,
我就把龙宫毁灭
I'll destroy the Dragon Palace.
除了哪吒和太乙外
Except for Nezha and Taiyi,
任何人不得离开陈塘关半步
no one is to leave Chen Tang Pass.
七天内取不到玉液琼浆
If the Elixir of Immortality isn't obtained within seven days,
或走漏半点龙族的风声
or if any news of the Dragon Clan leaks out,
我就让陈塘关鸡犬不留
I'll leave no one alive in Chen Tang Pass.
我信不过我的那三个兄妹
I don't trust my three siblings,
我也不能长时间灵魂出窍
and I can't be out of my body for long.
看守陈塘关
Guarding Chen Tang Pass
只有靠你了
falls to you.
嗯，对嘛，
Yes, that's right,
没有什么意思是点个头无法表达的
there's nothing that a nod can't convey.
李大人，大伙来给三少爷送行
Lord Li, everyone has come to see off the Third Young Master,
感谢他救了全城老小的性命
to thank him for saving the lives of all the townsfolk.
不敢当
You're too kind.
犬子这些年给大家添乱
My son has caused quite a bit of trouble for everyone over the years.
哎，老夫早看出三少爷必定大有作为
I foresaw that the Third Young Master would achieve great things.
大家瞧瞧
Look at him,
他天庭饱满面庞宽大
with a full forehead, broad face,
他的鼻梁丰起，脸腮鼓，嘴唇厚
a prominent nose, round cheeks, and thick lips.
此乃盖世英雄之面相
This is the face of a great hero.
老夫从不会看走眼
I never misjudge.
少爷饭后可得记得刷牙呀
Young Master, remember to brush your teeth after meals.
老大
Boss,
伏魔帮派从此时起改名为哪吒帮派
from now on, the Demon Suppression Gang will be renamed the Nezha Gang.
全体成员尊奉老大号令
All members will follow the Boss's orders.
少爷想练字吗？
Does Young Master want to practice calligraphy?
找我呀
Come to me.
少爷都三岁了
Young Master is three years old now.
是时候找个女朋友了
It's time to find a girlfriend.
想学乐器吗
Want to learn an instrument?
我们样样精通
We're experts at everything!
我想踢毽子
I want to play shuttlecock!
怎么了？
What's up?
很好玩的
It's so much fun!
没人踢毽子吗
No one to play shuttlecock?
我陪你
I'll play with you.
你不是一直想和爹踢毽子吗
Don't you always want to play with Dad?
ew！哪吒的力量有点大
Ew! Nezha, your kick is a bit too strong!
哈哈哈哈哈
Hahaha
我堂堂武将
I'm a mighty warrior!
哈哈哈
Haha
爹~哪吒不愧是我的儿子
Dad~ Nezha is my son, after all!
嗯啊啊
Mmm-hmm
要不改天再踢毽子吧？
How about we play another day?
你再说什么呢？
What are you talking about?
今天我们就要玩的尽兴
We're going to have a blast today!
我没事
I'm fine.
那我也要玩，夫人
I want to play too, Lady.
你又何苦？瞧不起我吗？
Why do you insist? Do you look down on me?
我也堂堂武将
I'm a mighty warrior too!
哪吒~接住这个
Nezha~ catch this!
你这孩子咋这都接不住呢
How can you not catch that, kid?
我不是魔丸就好了
If only I weren't the demon pill...
你说什么？没啥
What did you say? Nothing.
我也该出发了
I should be off now
你走之前能不能给娘一个大大的拥抱
Can you give your mom a big hug before you go?
哎
Oh
他们都看着呢
Everyone's watching
哎，等一等
Oh, wait a moment
这都是娘亲手做的好吃的
These are all the yummy treats I made
和你师傅在途中吃
To eat on the way with your master
哎，知道了知道了，我走了
Oh, I know, I know. I'm leaving
喂，我还没下来
Hey, I'm not down yet
而你的身体，还不够完善
And your body isn't fully developed yet
千万别乱用蛮力！知道了
Don't use brute force! Got it
你脾气大
You have a temper
但外遇时要冷静
But stay calm when you're out
爹娘不在身边
With no parents around
要学会照顾自己
Learn to take care of yourself
你这个家伙
You, mister
你就抱一下你娘怎么了？
What's wrong with giving your mom a hug?
你不觉的肉麻吗？又不是不会相见了，快快走
Don't you find it embarrassing? We'll see each other again soon, hurry up and go
哎，叹气干嘛？
Oh, why the sigh?
不好吃吗？
Is it not tasty?
吃吃吃，你就知道吃
Eat, eat, eat, all you think about is eating
我看看我，我都愁得吃不下了
Look at me, I'm so worried I can't even eat
你有没有想过怎么通过考核？
Have you thought about how to pass the test?
考核什么内容呀？
What kind of test?
考核你的道行够不够深啊
It tests if your skills are deep enough
你当着先监考官的面
You'll face the examiner
赤手空拳降服三只地线级别的妖王
And subdue three Earthline-level demon kings with your bare hands
打架，这我最擅长
Fighting, that's my specialty
只要你一发出魔气
As soon as you release your demonic aura
你身份就暴露了
Your cover's blown
那就老熬丙控制我身体呗
Then let Ao Bing take control of my body
用他的灵气我还不是一样厉害哦
With his spirit energy, I'll be just as powerful
你说的容易，我们来打一架试试
Easy for you to say. Let's see you do it
哪吒，你全身放松
Nezha, relax
让敖丙控制你的身体跟我切磋试试
Let Ao Bing take control of your body and spar with me
熬丙，你干啥
Ao Bing, what are you doing?
站稳点儿
Stand steady
灵魂依附在别人的身上，除非比宿主的精神力强大的多
Possessing someone's body only works if your spirit is much stronger
否则是控制不了宿主的身体
Otherwise, you can't control their body
呀
Uh!
哪吒你别急
Nezha, don't panic
你越使劲儿
The harder you struggle
熬丙就越会控制不了你的身体
The less control Ao Bing will have over your body
哎，你用腿啊
Hey, use your legs
绊倒他，绊倒他
Trip him, trip him
吼呵呵呵呵呵
Ha ha ha ha ha
不要怕，我来救.........你
Don't worry, I'll save... you
你玩的挺开心是吧？
Having fun, are you?
我们马上就到玉虚宫了，你还玩？
We're almost at the Jade Void Palace, and you're playing?
你瞧瞧你从头到脚
Look at you, from head to toe
你哪有个师傅的样子
You don't look like a master at all
站这里给我好好反省一下你自己
Stand there and reflect on your actions
想不出来办法我不让你吃饭
No dinner until you come up with a plan
你这么大个人了
You're a grown-up now
你一点二都不让人省心
You're such a handful
有办法了。催眠丹药
I've got it. Hypnotic pills
啥玩意儿
What's that?
吃了这个的话立刻就会睡着
Eat this, and you'll fall asleep right away.
你睡着以后熬丙就能完全控制你身体了
Once you're asleep, Ah Jing can take full control of your body.
妙哉
Brilliant!
哎哎哎，一颗药丸就够了
Oh no, one pill is enough!
你为什么不早点说。安静了
Why didn't you say so earlier? Quiet now.
师伯
Master.
这才像是正版的嘛
That's more like it.
怎么了师伯
What's wrong, Master?
没事没事
Nothing, nothing.
你已完全接管哪吒身体了，再试一下
You've taken full control of Nezha's body. Try it again.
师伯要动真的了
Master is getting serious.
你最好全力以赴
You'd better give it your all.
还请世伯多多指点
Please, Master, guide me.
还行吧
Not bad.
你勉强能跟我打平手
You can barely match me.
师傅，您流鼻血了啊
Master, you're bleeding from the nose!
哦，是上火而已，最近喝水少了
Oh, it's just a bit of heat. I haven't been drinking enough water lately.
哎呀，没事没事
Oh, it's nothing, nothing.
到昆仑山了
We've arrived at Kunlun Mountain.
这里的一天时间不会是其他地方的一年吧
Is a day here not a year elsewhere?
放心
Don't worry.
这还不是天
This isn't heaven yet.
这么多人都是来拜师修行的
All these people are here to learn and practice.
阐教名扬四海
The Teachings of the Complete Perfection are renowned across the seas.
世上的人无不向往
Everyone in the world aspires to them.
你看这个，绿色的佩玉
Look at this, the green jade pendant.
阐教仙人的凭证
It's the credential of a Complete Perfection Immortal.
有了它
With it,
我告诉你，走遍天下谁都会对你另眼相看。成仙真好
I'll tell you, everyone will look at you differently. Being an immortal is great.
你的两个哥哥都成仙了
Your two older brothers have become immortals.
你也没有问题哦
And you'll be fine too.
我是说哪吒的哥哥们
I mean Nezha's brothers.
他的两个哥都是三代弟子中的佼佼者
Both of his older brothers are outstanding among the third-generation disciples.
你知道吗？哪吒这个娃儿调皮的很
Do you know? Nezha is quite the troublemaker.
我就经讲他两个哥哥故事给他听
I often tell him stories about his two older brothers.
当正面榜样
To set a good example.
我跟你说啊
Let me tell you,
哪吒特别崇拜他的两个哥哥
Nezha really admires his two older brothers.
哎呦。你运气不错啊
Oh wow. You're lucky.
刚来就碰不上名满天下的捕妖队。捕妖队？
Just missed the famous monster-hunting team. Monster-hunters?
全靠他们四处征讨霍乱人间的妖怪
They keep the peace by battling the monsters that wreak havoc.
才保留天下太平
Thanks to them, the world remains safe.
捕妖队现任的头领
The current leader of the monster-hunters
他是我大师兄的大弟子
is the top disciple of my senior brother.
诶，我咋记得前一任头领还是申公豹呢？
Wait, didn't Shen Gongbao lead them last time?
师傅，那冒烟的是什么
Master, what's that smoking thing?
那是玉虚宫的镇宫之宝
That's the treasure of the Jade Void Palace.
天元鼎
The Celestial Cauldron.
哈哈哈，师弟好久不见呐
Hahaha, long time no see, little brother!
呵呵呵
Hehehe
大师兄
Senior Brother
听闻师尊闭关期间
During Master's seclusion,
由大师兄代为执掌玉虚宫
Senior Brother has been overseeing the Jade Void Palace.
我是带徒儿来参加升仙考核
I've brought my disciple to take the Immortal Ascension Exam.
哪吒还不快来拜见大师伯
Nezha, come and greet your Great Uncle!
拜见大师伯
Greeting Great Uncle.
你就是哪吒？你是灵珠转世的吧
So you're Nezha? You must be the reincarnation of the Spirit Pearl.
哎呀呀呀
Oh my!
了不得了不得
Incredible, incredible!
天尊可是对你寄予厚望啊
The Heavenly Lord has high hopes for you.
不愧为灵珠转世
No wonder you're the reincarnation of the Spirit Pearl.
瞧瞧瞧瞧
Look at that!
朝气蓬勃
Full of vigor and vitality.
一身正气
Radiating righteousness.
（打哈欠~）
(yawning~)
他最近练功过度
He's been overtraining lately.
状态有点不稳定
His condition is a bit unstable.
喂！你这个家伙在干什么？这是玉虚宫。我尿急
Hey! What are you doing? This is the Jade Void Palace. I really need to go!
鹤童
Crane Boy,
带小师侄去更衣
take the little nephew to change.
换什么衣服？
Change what?
我又没说要换衣服，你有病啊
I didn't say anything about changing clothes. Are you sick?
更衣意思就是带你去厕所里尿尿
"Change" means taking you to the bathroom to pee.
我这个徒儿很粗鲁
My disciple is a bit crude.
不要见怪
Don't mind him.
哇
Wow
好白
So white
啊，好白
Ah, so white
整个宫殿都是玉做的吗
Is the whole palace made of jade?
你们从哪来那么多钱买玉啊?
Where did you get all the money to buy jade?
玉虚宫名字的含义就是说用玉做的吧
The name Jade Void Palace means it's made of jade, right?
那虚这个名字里面的字啥意思啊
What does the "Xu" in the name mean?
是谦虚吗
Is it humility?
肾虚还是空虚
Kidney deficiency or emptiness?
对，厕所也是玉做的吧
Is the toilet made of jade too?
神仙也要用厕所啊？
Even immortals need bathrooms?
仙翁也会拉屎吗
Do the old immortals poop too?
清修之地禁止喧哗
No loud talking in this place of spiritual cultivation.
厕所还有多远啊
How much further to the bathroom?
快憋不住了
I can't hold it much longer.
喂，师姐，等等我
Hey, Senior Sister, wait for me!
呃，我不是故意的
Uh, I didn't mean to.
我要换裙子
I need to change my dress.
你自己去吧
You go on ahead.
我不知道厕所在哪啊
I don't know where the bathroom is.
穿过回廊右转再左转
Go through the corridor, turn right, then left
哇，不愧是神仙用的厕所
Wow, this must be where the gods go to the bathroom
太有品味了
So stylish!
嗯哼
Hmm
奇怪了
That's odd
咋回不去了啊
Why can't I get back?
你往哪走啊
Where are you going?
我迷路了
I'm lost
跟我来
Follow me
师弟将灵珠培育成才
My junior brother has nurtured the Spirit Pearl into a talent
可算为阐教立了大功一件了
He's truly done a great service for the Ch'an Sect
赞誉了，全靠师尊提携我
All thanks to Master's guidance
这昆仑甘露乃修仙补品
This Kunlun Dew is a divine elixir
原本半年才积的两一盆
It usually takes half a year to fill just one basin
今天叫你去看
I asked you to check it today
居然满了
And it's already full
来得早不如来得巧啊
Timing is everything
师弟，你说你是不是有福之人呐
Junior brother, you must be a lucky one
你抽风了？不会喝水了吗？
Are you having a seizure? Can't drink water anymore?
我这个徒弟粗鄙的很
My disciple is rather crude
莫怪莫怪
No offense, no offense
水里有我的尿
There's my pee in the water
我的师傅也挺粗鄙的
My master is pretty crude too
师兄，事不宜迟
Senior brother, we shouldn't delay
我看还是让哪吒参加考核吧
I think we should let Nezha take the exam
何必着急呀
Why rush?
多喝几杯再走啊
Have a few more drinks before you go
那不喝了不喝了
No, no more, thanks
呃
Uh
那也行吧
That works
嗯，那就派我的徒儿鹿童监考
Sure, I'll send my disciple, Lutong, to supervise
捕妖对着下一个目标
The next monster is up
就交给哪吒降服吧
Let Nezha handle it
师兄告辞
Farewell, Senior Brother
哎呀，我这个师弟还是这么急性子
Oh, my impatient junior brother
这次甘露的味道
The taste of this nectar
特别浓郁
Is especially rich
以后都要沿用这次的工艺。遵命
We should use this method from now on. Understood
怎么停了啊
Why did it stop?
都三个时辰了，道长
It's been three hours, Daoist
实在扔不动了
I really can't throw anymore
废物！修炼怎可懈怠
Worthless! How can you slack off in practice?
我不说停，你不准停
I didn't say to stop, you can't stop
陈塘关李靖求见。申道长
Li Jing of Chentang Pass requests an audience. Daoist Shen
昨日一战陈塘关军民伤者甚重
Many soldiers and civilians were injured in yesterday's battle
药物告罄
We're out of medicine
恳请道长开个通道
I humbly request you to open a passage
放几个大夫出城采买药物
To let a few doctors leave the city to buy medicine
好胆子
Bold move
不愧是......哪个混蛋?
Just as I expected... Which scoundrel?
你个王八蛋..
You jerk...
停...停....停.......
Stop... stop... stop.......
把刚才捉到那位带上来
Bring the one we just caught up
大战时从城里逃出来
He escaped from the city during the battle
劳烦李总兵
Commander Li, please
把他也带...带回去
Take him... take him back
误会啊
It's a misunderstanding
申道长
Daoist Shen
我也是妖怪呀
I'm a monster too
这海夜叉
This Sea Demon
我原本捉他来是为了还我儿子的清白
I caught him to clear my son's name
现在事情已了
Now it's all settled
他也没做什么伤天害理之事
He hasn't done anything truly wicked
就随他去吧
Let him be
嘿嘿嘿
Hehehe
就是就是，我是配角，小配角
Yeah, yeah, I'm just a minor character
哈哈，看来你是没听明白
Ha, looks like you didn't get it
我连只妖都不会放出去
I wouldn't let even a demon out
可况人
Let alone a human
道长开恩呐
Master, please have mercy
我也是妖啊
I'm a demon too
我们都是反派呀
We're all the bad guys
呸，谁..谁跟你是反派
Pfft, who... who said we're bad guys
知道灵珠秘密的都别想出去
No one who knows the secret of the Spirit Pearl can leave
若无药医治伤患
If there's no medicine to treat the injured
他们性命难保
Their lives are in danger
还望道长
I hope, Master
网开一面
Can you show some mercy
报，抓到一名奸细
Report, we've caught a spy
这人是从城外来的
This person came from outside the city
还伤了我们几个弟兄
And he hurt a few of our brothers
把他们关到城里面去
Lock them up inside the city
哥，是你吗？
Bro, is that you?
你？
You?
哥，是我啊
Bro, it's me
你是小生
You're Xiaosheng
申小豹（昵称）
Shen Xiaobao (nickname)
你100多年没回过家
You haven't been home for over a hundred years
我好想你啊
I've missed you so much
你怎么来了
How did you get here?
爹叫我来找你啊
Dad sent me to find you
瞧，你送我的罗盘
Look, the compass you gave me
能测你的位置
It can track your location
哦。哦
Oh. Oh.
爹，他老人家还好吗
How's Dad doing?
好着呢
He's doing great
自从你进了玉虚宫
Ever since you joined the Jade Void Temple
爹就跟吃了大补丸似的
Dad's been as perky as a puppy
天天倍儿精神
Full of energy every day
我们七山五岭可就出了你一个禅教仙人
You're the only Zen Immortal from our seven mountains and five ridges
十里八乡的妖族都争着拜爹为师呢
All the demons from the neighboring villages want Dad to be their master
对了
By the way
你来找我干吧
Why did you come looking for me?
你以前不是说过
Didn't you say before
等我修炼成人形
Once I can transform into a human
就引荐我进玉虚宫吗
You'd introduce me to the Jade Void Temple?
我会变人嘞
I can transform now
这些年我天天都用功
I've been studying hard every day
从没偷过懒。
I've never slacked off
哥就是我的榜样
Big Brother is my role model
玉虚名门济天下
The Jade Void Temple helps the world
替天行道走四方
Upholding justice everywhere
哎，对了，哥
Hey, Big Brother
你在这干嘛呀
What are you doing here?
我........这些海妖都是你部下吗
Are... are these sea demons your subordinates?
你们把陈塘关围起来干啥
Why are you surrounding Chen Tang Pass?
那个嘛
Well, um...
这....就是........申道长在守卫陈塘关啊
This... is Daoist Master Shen guarding the town of Chentang.
因有邪魔外道来犯
There's a threat from evil forces.
申道长率海族前来守城
Master Shen leads the sea creatures to defend the city.
我代全城百姓拜谢道长之义举
I speak for all the townsfolk, thanking you for your noble act.
好说好说
No problem, no problem.
哇，哥，你太了不起了
Wow, bro, you're amazing!
这就是袭击陈塘关的妖怪吗
So these are the monsters attacking Chentang?
妖族的名声都被你们败光了
You guys are ruining the reputation of all demons.
败类。那个...小豹子
Scum. Hey... little leopard.
你能不能等几年再上玉虚宫啊
Can you wait a few years before going to Jade Void Palace?
为什么？我会变成人了啊
Why? I can turn into a human now.
哈哈，最近我准备晋升12金仙
Ha, I'm preparing to ascend to the 12 Golden Immortals.
不能分心
Can't afford to be distracted.
12金仙？事成之后再带你..好吗?
12 Golden Immortals? How about after I succeed, then I'll take you... okay?
没事，哥，晋级重要
No worries, bro, leveling up is important.
我什么时候上玉虚宫都一样
It doesn't matter when I go to Jade Void Palace.
反正我变人还不熟练
Besides, I'm not great at being human yet.
回去再练练
I'll practice more.
再练练
Practice more.
小豹子
Little leopard.
这是我进玉虚宫后攒的
This is what I've saved up since joining Jade Void Palace.
这什么呀
What's this?
玉虚宫给所有弟子定期发放仙丹
Jade Void Palace regularly gives out elixirs to all disciples.
吃一颗，相当于10年苦修
One pill is worth ten years of hard practice.
哇！这..这太宝贵了
Wow! This... this is so precious!
哥，你在晋级还是你吃
Bro, are you taking it or should you eat it?
你吃，我吃不惯这个
You eat it, I'm not used to this stuff.
就喜欢自己修炼
I prefer to practice on my own.
你..你拿回去
You... take it back
家里人分着吃
Share it with your family
不行不行
No, no
爹肯定会怪我
Dad will blame me
小豹不听哥话了？
Little Leopard, not listening to your brother?
带上仙丹快走
Take the elixir and go
这是前线，再...再不走
This is the front line. If... if you don't leave
影响我指挥
It'll affect my command
那...我...
Well... I...
走啦
Go on
哥，你一定要当上12金仙
Brother, you must become one of the 12 Golden Immortals
我也会继续努力的
I'll keep working hard too
你虽帮了我
Though you helped me
但事关重大
This is a serious matter
我还是不能放人走，这个夜叉
I can't let this Naga go
你....你也带回去
You... you take it back too
我帮的不是你
I didn't help you
而是那个少年
I helped that young boy
一个好的榜样
A good role model
能改变他的一生
Can change his life
等一下
Wait a moment
留下....留下药材清单
Leave... leave the list of herbs
我乃哪吒三太子
I am the Third Prince Nezha
能降妖来会作诗
I can subdue demons and write poems
今日到此除奸恶
Today I've come to purge the evil
尔等妖孽快受死
You wicked creatures, prepare to die
还在吃？我降服你们来了
Still eating? I'm here to tame you
谁吃了熊心豹子胆？
Who ate the heart of a bear and the gall of a leopard?
敢来土肥坡来撒野啊
To dare cause trouble in Tufei Slope
哈哈嘿，你就是床
Ha ha he, you're the bed
来来来，领教下小爷我的手段
Come on, come on, taste my skills
嘿，小屁孩你怎么这么狂？
Hey, little brat, why are you so cocky?
大哥给他点颜色瞧瞧
Big brother, show him some color
出招吧
Show your moves
你上，不..不..不...不..大哥
You go, no... no... no... no... Big Brother
小弟怎么能跟你抢风头呢
How can I steal the spotlight from you?
跟小屁孩打架多没面子
Fighting a little kid would be so embarrassing.
叫你上你就上
Just go when I tell you to.
小...小....小屁孩
Litt... lit... little kid
看你小不懂事
Look at you, so clueless.
咱也不跟你计较
I won't even bother with you.
你你你你你
Y-y-y-you
现在你想回家还来急
Now you want to go home, too late.
咋回事
What's going on?
你怎么又醒了
Why are you awake again?
不知道啊
I don't know.
睡的轻，你动了几下就给我吵醒了
I sleep lightly. Your movements woke me up.
糟了，这下好了
Uh-oh, here we go.
他上次药吃多了，有了抗药性
He took too much medicine last time and built up a resistance.
加大药量
Increase the dosage.
再不走我不客气了
I'll be serious if you don't leave.
我想往右躲避
I tried to dodge to the right.
抱歉，我以为要向左
Sorry, I thought we were going left.
哼哼哼哼
Huh huh huh huh
这么不耐打
So weak!
师伯，还是我上吧
Master, let me give it a try.
师弟需要多练几年再来晋级
Junior needs more years of practice before he can step up.
你再等一哈
Just wait a bit longer.
他在跟妖怪开玩笑
He's joking with the monster.
我这个徒弟就是...就是爱装逼
My disciple is... just a show-off.
药，药，药
Med... med... medicine
我得吃药啊
I need to take my medicine.
让你走你不走
I told you to leave when you had the chance.
现在知道小爷厉害了吧
Now you know how awesome I am.
糟了，药都化进汤里了
Oh no, the medicine dissolved in the soup.
那我就喝汤
Then I'll just drink the soup.
还敢偷我们的汤喝，你欠打
Stealing our soup? You're asking for it!
让我来
Let me handle it.
太恶心了，大力金刚棒
That's disgusting, Great Power Staff!
你看，我说他是演的吧
See, I told you he was just acting.
刚才是大意了
I was just careless earlier.
不算数
That doesn't count.
不可能！不可能
Impossible! Impossible!
你咋这么笨啊
How can you be so clueless?
一边二带着，看我怎么教训他
Watch me teach him a lesson.
你怎么全吐了呀
Why did you throw it all up?
味道太冲了
It was too overpowering.
实在没忍住。看招
I couldn't hold it in. Here goes nothing!
戏精
Drama queen.
不行啊只有吃药才会胜算
We need to take the medicine to win.
鹿童在这儿，我没法给你药啊
With Lutong here, I can't give you the medicine.
怎么办，怎么办
What do we do, what do we do?
有
There is.
还有一个办法
There's another way.
你该不会是想
You can't be thinking of...
把吐了的全吃回来。这...这怎么能行
Eating it all back? This... This can't be right.
怕什么，我连夜叉的鼻涕都喝过
What's to fear? I've even drunk the booger juice of a trident.
原来如此
I see.
能忍下常人不能忍的
To endure what others cannot.
哪吒果然是不认命
Nezha truly refuses to accept his fate.
我肩负父母朋友的性命啊
I bear the lives of my parents and friends.
陈塘关百姓的安危
The safety of the people of Chentang Pass.
受这点罪又算什么
Suffering a little is nothing.
无视世俗之偏见
Ignoring the prejudices of the world.
突破心中之魔障
Breaking through the mental barriers.
我要扭转命运
I will change my destiny.
以前我就是低调而已，今天为大家显露一点
I've always been low-key. Today, I'll show you all a bit.
师伯，先救哪吒
Master, save Nezha first.
玉液琼浆只有另想办法了
We'll have to find another way for the elixir.
没道理啊
That doesn't make sense.
我不信
No way!
小屁孩，再跟我打一场
Hey, brat, let's have another go!
装死吗？我打死你
Playing possum? I'll knock you out!
多亏哪吒被打晕了
Good thing Nezha got knocked out.
我说你笨你还不服气
I said you were dense, and you just couldn't accept it.
看我来替你报仇
Watch me avenge you!
无敌旋风拳
Invincible Cyclone Punch!
全都得抓吗
Do we have to catch them all?
即使留下一只也会祸害这里的百姓
Even one left behind could cause trouble for the locals.
都带回玉虚宫
Take them all back to the Jade Void Palace.
本教会将他们引入正道
Our sect will guide them onto the right path.
改邪归正
Turn over a new leaf.
师弟的样子
My junior brother's look...
哎，没事没事，哈哈
Oh, don't worry, ha ha!
他就是一会儿丑一会儿帅。灵珠嘛
He's a bit of a mood swing, you know. Spirit Pearl and all.
肯定跟正常人不一样噻
He's bound to be different from the rest of us.
下回稳当点二
Next time, be a bit more careful, okay?
灵魂都被你吓跑了
You scared the living daylights out of me!
哎呦，这小孩是谁啊
Whoa, who's this kid?
听说叫哪吒
They say his name is Nezha.
金吒、木吒的弟弟
Jinzha and Muzha's little brother.
他是天尊钦定的灵珠转世
He's the reincarnation of the Spirit Pearl, chosen by the Heavenly Master.
哦哦
Oh, I see.
就这小孩啊
This kid?
但形象可不咋样
But he doesn't look too impressive.
弓腰驼背
Hunched back and all.
脚步轻浮
Kind of bouncy on his feet.
低眉垂眼
Eyes downcast and droopy.
相貌猥琐
Looks rather creepy
还带黑眼圈
And has dark circles under his eyes
长得跟个鬼似的
Looks like a ghost
不要招惹是非啊
Don't stir up trouble
师弟
Junior Brother
你瞧，今晚是何星象
Look, what's the night sky like tonight?
六星连珠
Six stars in a row
十年一遇
Happens once every ten years
每逢六星连珠
Whenever the six stars align
这白玉台就可以万里传送音像
This jade platform can transmit images and sounds over vast distances
众师弟遍布天下
Junior brothers are scattered across the world
难得一聚
It's rare for us to gather
今日正好借六星连珠之机会
Today, we can use the alignment of the six stars
开一次金仙大会
To hold a Golden Immortal Assembly
我还没晋升12金仙
I haven't yet ascended to the Twelve Golden Immortals
我还是回避比较好
I should probably avoid it
早晚的事！不得行！不得行
It's only a matter of time! No, no!
这怎么可以呢，我还是回避吧
How can I, I should avoid it
使不得！使不得啊
No way! No way!
那你咋坐上去的
How did you get up there then?
你闭嘴，你见不得你师傅好吗？
Shut up, can't you stand to see your master?
这是桑拿呀
This is a sauna
恭迎各位师弟归位
Welcome all junior brothers back
参见大师兄
Greetings, Senior Brother
给大家引荐一位新成员
Let me introduce a new member
太乙师弟
Junior Brother Taiyi
他不负师尊所托
He has not let our master down
已将灵珠转世培育成才
We've nurtured the Spirit Pearl into a talented being
行礼
Bow
封神大战迫在眉睫
The Great Battle for the Gods is imminent
此次会议须得商讨备战事情
This meeting must discuss our preparations for battle
阐教乃道统正宗
The Orthodox Daoist Sect must lead the way
此战必胜
Victory is assured
但近年来截教崛起迅猛
But in recent years, the Unorthodox Sect has risen rapidly
不得不防
We must be cautious
哼哼
Humph
截教尽是披毛带角之人
The Unorthodox Sect is full of hairy, horned creatures
湿生卵化之辈
Born from dampness and eggs
此战关乎本门兴旺
This battle concerns the prosperity of our sect
不得掉以轻心
We cannot afford to be complacent
增强本教实力
Strengthening our sect's power
方是根本。正是如此
Is the foundation. Indeed, it is
为此，老夫早早便开始了准备
For this, I have been preparing for a long time
仙丹共有9000枚
There are 9,000 immortal pills
可按级别高低分发给众门人
They can be distributed to disciples based on their rank
本教实力势必大大提升
Our sect's strength will surely increase greatly
怎么有这么多
How can there be so many?
近百年来
For nearly a century,
恩师一直以天元鼎加紧炼丹
Master has been diligently refining elixirs with the Celestial Cauldron.
日夜不息
Day and night, without rest.
连自己的修炼都落下了
He's even neglected his own cultivation.
大师兄为阐教兴衰殚精竭虑
Senior Brother has been exhausting himself for the prosperity of the Orthodox Sect.
劳苦功高
His efforts are truly commendable.
除了截教
Apart from the截教,
可还有无其他妖邪图谋不轨
are there any other evil forces plotting against us?
禀师叔，一旦发现厉害妖孽
Uncle Master, whenever a powerful demon is detected,
补妖队便前往收服
the Demon Capture Squad goes to subdue it.
所以一般散妖都不成气候
So, most scattered demons don't pose a threat.
但还有只妖族除外
But there is one exception.
哪只妖族
Which one?
东海龙族啊
The Dragon Clan of the Eastern Sea.
龙族不是早已归降天庭了吗
Haven't the dragons already surrendered to the Heavenly Court?
非我族类，其心必异
Those not of our kind must have ulterior motives.
在我看来
In my opinion,
他们的归降只是虚与委蛇
their surrender is just a pretense.
等待时机
They are waiting for the right moment.
龙族千年来镇压海底妖兽有功
The Dragon Clan has been suppressing sea monsters for a thousand years.
何罪之有呢
What crime have they committed?
但他们实力太强
But they are too powerful.
若封神之战时倒戈
If they betray us during the battle for the divine positions,
恐会影响整个战局
it could sway the entire war.
还是不可
We cannot take that risk.
本教名门正派之名深入人心
Our sect's reputation as a righteous and noble school is well-established.
若师出无名
If we act without just cause,
无故讨伐降将
and unjustly attack those who have surrendered,
将来还靠什么取信天下
how will we gain the trust of the world?
言之有理
That's a valid point.
不可以轻举妄动，此事还要从长计议
We cannot act rashly. We must deliberate further.
但是，行了
But, let's go.
大家所言在理
Everyone makes a good point.
你也不必执拗了
No need to be stubborn.
是！六星连珠时辰将尽
Yes! The alignment of the six stars is almost over.
目下也无其他议题
There's no other business to discuss.
那就散会吧
Let's adjourn the meeting.
师兄
Senior Brother.
金吒、木吒分别拜于我和普贤师弟门下
Jinzha and Muzha are studying under me and my junior brother Puxian.
修行多年未曾归乡
They haven't returned home in years.
连哪吒这个三弟也素未谋面
They've never even met their youngest brother, Nezha.
六星连珠尚有片刻时间
The alignment of the six stars still has a bit of time left.
不如借此机会
Why not take this opportunity
让他们兄弟三人一聚
to bring the three brothers together?
好主意
Great idea!
怎么办
What do we do?
咋整咋整
What should we do?
你怎么了
What's wrong with you?
你说我的这形象会不会给人的第一印象不太好啊
Do you think my appearance might give a bad first impression?
肯定不会啊
Not at all!
真的吗？
Really?
虽然你仪态懒散
Though you look lazy,
但意志坚定
your will is strong.
虽然你个头矮小
Though you're small in stature,
但内心强大
your heart is mighty.
虽然你相貌丑陋
Though you're not much to look at,
但心地善良啊
you have a kind heart.
虽然你眼眶发黑
Though your eyes are a bit dark,
鼻孔朝天
and your nose points to the sky,
牙还缺了一颗
and you're missing a tooth,
但我觉得你就是很好很好啊
I think you're just wonderful.
你兄长一定也会这么想的
Your brothers would think so too.
我真是谢谢你的夸奖啊
Thank you so much for your kind words.
你干嘛？你替我去见哥哥。这怎么能行
What are you doing? You can't go see my brother for me. That's not right.
这种事怎么能替啊
You can't replace me in this.
不行啊
No way.
哪吒！哪吒
Nezha! Nezha!
这孩子还害羞了
The kid is blushing!
哈哈哈哈
Hahaha
哪吒，三弟
Nezha, Third Brother
你哭了
You're crying.
我刚才想起了我两个哥哥
I just thought of my two brothers.
你也有哥哥
You have brothers too?
以前
Back then,
有两个这么好的哥哥
having two such great brothers
真幸福啊
was truly a blessing.
刚刚你们聊了些啥呀
What did you talk about just now?
他们说
They said
很抱歉他们一直没机会回去看看你
they're sorry they haven't had the chance to visit you.
他们问这些年家里怎么样了
They asked how things have been at home.
父母是否安康
Are our parents well?
有什么爱好
What are your hobbies?
有哪些朋友
Who are your friends?
他们还说
They also said
今后无论遇到什么困难
No matter what difficulties you face in the future
都要告诉他们
You should tell them
让你记得你的两个哥哥永远都会帮助你，保护你
Remember, your two older brothers will always be there to help and protect you
你怎么也哭了
Why are you crying too?
眼睛里的沙子
Just got something in my eye
这次不是沙子里进眼睛了
This time it's not just something in my eye
你讨厌啊，我都说不是了
You're so annoying, I already said it's not
你说不是就不是
If you say it's not, then it's not
不理你了
I'm not talking to you
好好好
Okay, okay
我不笑了，不笑了
I won't laugh, I won't laugh
你还在生气呢
You're still mad
哪吒，哪吒
Nezha, Nezha
我从小就暴戾放纵
I've been wild and unruly since I was a child
爹娘为我操碎了心
My parents have worried about me endlessly
你爹虽围困了陈塘关
Though your father has besieged Chen Tang Pass
但我知道他也是为了你才不顾一切
I know he did it all for you, without a second thought
你今天哥哥们也对我这么好
Today, your brothers have been so good to me
家人为我们付出了太多
Our family has sacrificed so much for us
你是妖
You are a demon
我是魔
I am a monster
是我们拖累了他们
We are the ones who have burdened them
天生妖魔又怎样
So what if we were born as demons and monsters?
是魔是仙
Whether we are monsters or immortals
我今后就得我自己来选
From now on, I'll choose for myself
等救了你以后，我们一定要得道成仙
Once you're saved, we'll become immortals together
不再让家人操心
No more worries for our family
对！成了仙才能堂堂正正的活下去
Yes! Only as immortals can we live with pride
说定了！小爷就要当神仙
It's a deal! I'm going to be a god
勇猛精进方能一日千里
With courage and determination, we'll soar
照你们这样再修百年也是枉然
At this rate, a hundred years of practice will be in vain
修仙修仙！首先修练的就是精气神
To cultivate immortality, first hone your spirit and energy
觉得苦，觉得累
When it's tough, when it's hard
要恨就恨你们为什么生来就是妖
Blame fate for making you a demon
拼尽全力才有机会逆天改命
Give it your all to defy destiny
得道成仙
Achieve immortality
从来生死都看淡
Always face life and death with calm
专和老天对着干
Defy the heavens at every turn
我命由我不由天
My fate is in my hands, not the heavens
小爷非要当神仙
I'm determined to be a god
短短几句便振聋发聩
A few short lines, yet so powerful
鼓舞人心
Truly inspiring
好诗好诗
What a poem, what a poem
这首诗的精神值得你们所有人学习
The spirit of this poem is worth learning from
是吗
Is it?
有那么好吗
Is it that good?
我自己瞎编的
I just made it up
非也非也
Not at all, not at all
字字珠玑，催人上进
Every word is a gem, urging us forward
能做出这样的诗
To write such poetry
可见你小小年纪就志存高远
Shows you have great ambition even at your young age
真是少年英雄
Truly a young hero
前途无量啊
With a bright future ahead
哎呦，我没那么好
Oh, I'm not that great
其实还是有些小缺陷啦
I still have some flaws, you know
你的缺陷大了去了
Your flaws are bigger than you think
我问你
I ask you
你那黑眼圈怎么回事啊
What's with those dark circles under your eyes?
我一看便知你经常熬夜
I can tell you stay up late often
你时常熬夜
You frequently stay up late
生活没规律
Your lifestyle is irregular
饮食不健康
Your diet is unhealthy
连起码的自律都做不到
You can't even manage basic self-discipline
你也配修仙？
And you think you're fit to practice cultivation?
我黑眼圈天生的。长相由心生你懂不懂？
My dark circles are natural. Looks come from within, you know?
自己拿镜子照照
Go look in a mirror
怪样子，吊儿郎当
You look sloppy and lazy
你要是我的徒弟
If you were my disciple
肯定教你重修人形
I'd definitely teach you to improve your appearance
可以重修？
Can it be improved?
你我的形象还有救了？
Can our appearances be fixed?
你教教我呗
Teach me, please
我早就知道你是来拜师的
I knew you came to be my disciple
这样吧小鬼
Alright, kid
我看你也是志向远大
I see you have great aspirations
就收了你这个徒弟啊
I'll take you as my disciple
师傅
Master
来跟师兄们一起练
Come practice with your senior brothers
修炼什么？修仙啊
What kind of practice? Cultivation, of course
修仙不用你教
I don't need you to teach me cultivation
你教我怎么美颜
Teach me how to beautify my face
混账
Jerk
修仙不学
I'm not studying cultivation
你学美颜
You study beautification
舍本逐末
Missing the forest for the trees
你到底教不教啊
Are you going to teach me or not?
从此我们断绝师徒关系
From now on, we are no longer master and apprentice
活该你当一辈子熊猫眼
Serves you right to be a panda eye for life
过分了啊
That's going too far
本来我还准备下手轻点干啥
I was planning to go easy on you
干嘛？踢馆吗？三颗应该够了。
What for? To kick me out? Three should be enough.
小鬼，你从哪儿来的回到哪儿去
Kid, go back to where you came from
再干扰我们正常教学
If you keep disrupting our classes
我可要动粗了
I'll have to get rough
得罪
Offend
你不是我对手
You're no match for me
好小子，我小看你了
Good one, I underestimated you
教训这个无知的小儿，师傅必胜。好快的身法
Teach this ignorant brat a lesson, Master will win. What fast moves!
你看清楚没得
Did you see that?
我们并无深仇大恨
We have no deep grudges
你还是回去吧
You should just go back
我不能败
I can't lose
你连碰都碰不到我
You can't even touch me
怎么跟我斗
How do you think you can beat me?
聪明！不放开他
Smart! Don't let him go
即使他的速度再快也没用
Even if he's fast, it won't help
还不投降？
Still not giving up?
原来你是！！！发现了？
So you are!!! Did you figure it out?
我并非是动作快
It's not that I'm fast
而是身体能化作电流
But that my body can turn into electricity
瞬间传导到任何位置，所以在水里我是无敌的
Instantly conducting to any part, so I'm invincible in water
好厉害的寒气
What a powerful chill
小心点啊
Be careful!
力气太大了肉身会崩溃的
Too much force will tear the body apart.
冰不导电
Ice doesn't conduct electricity.
看你还有什么能耐
Let's see what else you've got.
（咒语）ABCDEFHIGKLMN
(Spell) ABCDEFHIGKLMN
OPQRSTUVWXYZ
糟了，下雨的咒语！速战速决
Oh no, the rain spell! We need to finish this fast.
师傅！师傅你怎么了！师傅！我并非取你性命
Master! Master, what's wrong with you! Master, I didn't mean to take your life.
你又何苦自断一臂
Why did you have to cut off your own arm?
众弟子听令
Disciples, listen to me.
将妖孽押解回宫
Take the monster back to the palace.
住手，放下！都给我放下
Stop! Put it down! Everyone, put it down!
敢问阁下是否阐教门人
May I ask if you are a disciple of the Chanyu Sect?
是的，我是
Yes, I am.
这都是玉虚宫的仙长
These are all the immortals from the Jade Void Palace.
尔等不得无礼
You must not be disrespectful.
我等进了玉虚宫
Once we enter the Jade Void Palace,
就能接受正道教化
we can receive proper guidance.
未尝不是好事
It might not be a bad thing.
尔等都把兵刃给我扔了
All of you, drop your weapons.
爹爹
Dad
小豹你怎么回来了
Little Leopard, how did you come back?
小豹，你不能这么没有礼貌，肆意伤人
Little Leopard, you can't be so rude and hurt people.
胆敢伤我门人
How dare you harm my disciples!
不要
No!
爹
Dad
哪吒快封冻河水
Nezha, freeze the river!
你想往哪里逃
Where do you think you're running to?
爹！走！快走！
Dad! Run! Hurry!
逃啊
Run!
你们逃不掉的
You can't escape.
让开，他只是救父心切
Stand aside, he's just trying to save his father.
何苦下此重手
Why go to such lengths?
三七（药材）和黄茜（药材）
Notoginseng and turmeric
冰片（药材）
Borneol
再来一框
Another box, please
（药材）
(herb)
李大人，清单上的全齐了
Sir Li, everything on the list is here
另外还多了100筐鱼虾水产
Plus an extra 100 crates of fish and seafood
城里正好缺粮草啊
The city is in dire need of supplies
申道长留步
Daoist Shen, please stay
我们备了些酒菜
We've prepared some wine and dishes
道长可否赏脸一聚
Could you join us?
你？承蒙李大人开恩
Me? Thanks to Sir Li's kindness
收留我当了个差役
I've been taken in as a servant
他虽是妖
Though he's a demon
但心地不坏
His heart isn't bad
只要安分守己
As long as he behaves
未尝没有个好的归宿
There might be a good home for him
不知合不合道长口味
I wonder if it suits your taste
不.....不错啊
Not... bad at all
那您多吃些
Then please, help yourself
这酒你也尝尝
Try this wine too
我早就戒了
I gave it up long ago
修仙者需要克制....克制欲念
Cultivators must restrain... their desires
有言道，剪情欲则神全
It is said, cutting off lust leads to a whole spirit
亦有言道，行善道则德全
And it is also said, walking the path of kindness leads to a whole virtue
多说无用
Talking more is pointless
我早已无路可退
I have no way out
隐瞒逃避不是长久之计
Hiding and escaping is not a long-term solution
终有事情败露的一天
Eventually, the truth will come to light
若残害生灵，错上加错
If you harm living beings, you compound your mistakes
就算瞒天过海，也心障难除
Even if you deceive the world, you can't deceive your own heart
往后的修行
Future cultivation
更难有寸进
Will be even harder to advance
修仙的根本乃是积善德
The essence of cultivation is to accumulate good deeds
行正道
To walk the righteous path
住口
Enough
什么行善积德
What good deeds and virtue
你对修仙一无所知
You know nothing about cultivation
有人求见申道长
Someone wishes to see Master Shen
哥~！！
Bro~!!
小豹你怎么伤成这样
Little Leopard, how did you get so hurt
一帮道士围攻咱家
A bunch of Taoists attacked our home
爹他，还被人砍断了
Dad, he was even cut
手臂
His arm
谁砍的
Who did it
那个人叫...
The person is called...
哪吒
Nezha
恭喜师弟过了第二关
Congratulations, Junior Brother, on passing the second test
还请通禀无量师兄
Please inform Senior Brother Wu Liang
师傅今日闭关炼丹尚未出关
Master is in closed meditation refining elixirs and hasn't emerged yet
第三次考核前
Before the third test
师弟不如先休养几日
Junior Brother, why don't you rest for a few days
我们只剩下两天喽
We only have two days left
不用，我精神抖擞，接着考核
No need, I'm feeling great, ready for the next test
那也好
Very well then
最后一只妖王是骷髅山的石矶
The last demon king is from Skull Mountain, Stone矶 (Note: Stone矶 is a name and is directly transliterated as "Stone Ji")
殿外有人急事求见太乙仙长
Someone outside the hall urgently requests to see Master Taiyi
不好啦
Oh no!
陈塘关出事啦
Something's happened in Chentang Pass!
爹，娘，爹
Dad, Mom, Dad
娘
Mom
不要急不要急
Don't panic, don't panic
我们再找找，再找找
Let's look around some more, just a bit more
我刚从出关收到急报
I just received an urgent report
到底是何人犯下如此滔天罪行
Who could have committed such a heinous crime?
启禀师傅
Master, I report
据结界兽所说
According to the boundary beast
事前他们遭受巨大力量冲击
They were hit by an enormous force before the incident
失去知觉
They lost consciousness
醒来时发现陈塘关已被屠城
When they woke up, they found Chentang Pass had been massacred
还没得到玉液琼浆啊
But we haven't obtained the elixir yet
他们怎么会动手啊
Why would they attack?
师弟啊
Little brother
你可有头绪啊
Any leads?
没得没得
No, nothing
我是在想这些岩浆是从哪里来的
I'm trying to figure out where this lava is coming from
是啊
Yes
方圆千里没有火山
There are no volcanoes for miles around
当真匪夷所思啊
It's truly baffling
大家快来
Everyone, come quick
是何妖物
What kind of monster is this?
这是
This is
龙族爪印
A dragon's claw mark
不可能
Impossible
全体龙族都在东海龙宫镇守锁妖阵法
All the dragons are guarding the demon-sealing formation in the Eastern Sea Dragon Palace
一条都不可能离得开
Not a single one could have left
师父，弟子没记错的话
Master, if I recall correctly
关押在海底的西海龙王敖润
the Dragon King of the West Sea, Ao Run, who is imprisoned underwater
是否有种特殊技能
has a special skill
叫做裂
called
裂空爪
the Sky-Splitting Claw
你是说她用裂空爪穿越到了陈塘关
You mean she used the Sky-Splitting Claw to travel to Chen Tang Pass
这些岩浆便就说得通了
That would explain the lava
必是从海底炼狱隔空传送而来
It must have been teleported from the underwater prison
但她被东海龙王镇压在狱中
But she's sealed away by the Dragon King of the East Sea
不可能穿越至此啊
There's no way she could get here
那就只剩一种可能了
There's only one other possibility
弟子最担心的是
What I feared the most
还是发生了
has come to pass
东海龙王叛变
The Dragon King of the East Sea has betrayed us
此事牵连重大
This is a serious matter
会不会是我们猜错了
Could we be wrong about this
不会错
No, we're not wrong
就是他们
It's them
你要干什么
What are you going to do
不要冲动
Don't act rashly
你是要去龙宫吗
Are you going to the Dragon Palace
那是骷髅山的方向啊
That's the direction of Skull Mountain
龙族屠戮无辜百姓
The dragons have slaughtered innocent people
犯下这滔天恶行
committing heinous crimes
无需再通过金仙大会
We don't need to wait for the Immortal Assembly
老夫要先斩后奏
I'll act first and report later
鹤童，随我回宫
Crane Boy, come with me back to the palace
召集补妖队全体成员
Gather all the monster hunters
遵命！师弟
As you command! Junior Brother
哪吒父母被妖族所害
Nezha's parents were killed by the demon clan
不能再让这孩子有个三长两短
We can't let anything happen to this child
你与鹿童赶紧去接应他
You and Deer Boy go and meet him
遵命
As you command
我知道你现在很难过
I know you're going through a tough time
你可不可以
Can you
先冷静一下
please calm down for a bit
你能不能先带我回龙宫
Can you take me back to the Dragon Palace first
我会向父王和师父问个明白
I'll get to the bottom of this with Father and Master.
问明白就能救活我爹娘吗？
Will that bring my parents back to life?
镜子，镜子告诉我
Mirror, mirror, tell me true
谁是方圆十里最美的女人
Who's the fairest in the land?
是你！我的主人啊
It's you, my master!
那谁是方圆百里最美的女人
Who's the fairest in a hundred miles?
是你！我的主人
It's you, my master!
那方圆千里呢
What about a thousand miles?
是你
It's you.
万里呢
How about ten thousand miles?
是你！
It's you!
全天下呢？
The whole world?
还是你
Still you.
呸，你敷衍谁呢
Pfft, you're just being lazy.
你靠谱点行吗
Can you be a bit more serious?
没，没
No, no
这不怕您生气吗
Aren't you afraid I'll get mad?
我告诉你
Listen to me,
你说真话，我反而不生气
If you tell the truth, I won't be angry.
真不生气？
Not at all?
虽然石矶娘娘我貌美如花
Though I, Lady Stone, am as beautiful as a flower
但山外有山的道理
I do understand the principle that there's always someone better
我岂能不懂！！
How could I not?!
那你问吧
Go ahead, ask away
我是不是全天下最美的女人
Am I the most beautiful woman in the world?
不是！
No!
这才真实嘛
That's the truth, right?
我是不是方圆万里最美的女人呀
Am I the most beautiful woman within a thousand miles?
方圆千里呢
How about within a hundred miles?
不是！百里呢
No! What about within a hundred li?
不是！十里啊
No! What about within ten li?
不是
No
那我是不是这座山里最美的女人
Am I the most beautiful woman in this mountain?
不是啊
No
你骗鬼啊
You're kidding me
这座山里除了我根本没其他人
There's no one else in this mountain except me
我也是女的
And I am a woman too
你说过不生气的
You said you wouldn't get mad
你哪点比我漂亮
What makes you prettier than me?
救命啊！！你哪点比我漂亮？
Help! What makes you prettier than me?!
石妖何在
Where is the stone demon?
什么石妖不石妖的，叫我石矶娘娘
What stone demon? Call me Lady Stone!
臭小子，我们见过吗
Brat, have we met before?
你跟老娘我拼什么命啊
Why are you fighting me to the death?
你会暴露的
You'll expose yourself
让我来了！你上来
Let me handle it! Get up here!
你不要管
You don't need to worry
石矶娘娘我是多么容易被打败的吗
Do you really think I, Lady Stone, am that easy to defeat?
这座山都是老娘我的身体
This mountain is my very body
看你怎么灭的了我？
Let's see how you can destroy me!
再用力
Put more effort into it
你身体会崩的
Your body will crumble
我说~不需要你管
I said, it's none of your business
已经交手了
We've already engaged
糟了糟了
Oh no, oh no
要了命了
This is life-threatening
还好剩一点点
Luckily, there's still a bit left
留的青山在不怕没柴烧
As long as the青山remains, there's always hope
臭小子，给老娘我记着
Brat, you'll remember this
九龙神火罩
Nine-Dragon Divine Fire Hood
跑不脱
You can't escape
哎呀，你怎么那么冲动呀
Oh, why are you so impulsive?
肉身都差点崩溃了
Your physical body nearly collapsed
你不要命了呀
Are you trying to get yourself killed?
刚才的火焰是怎么回事啊
What was that fire about?
师弟不是冰系的吗
Isn't Junior Brother an ice-type?
我..我说他是冰系的
I... I said he's an ice-type
冰系火系我都教过
I've taught both ice and fire types
他练的是
He practices
冰火两重天
Ice and Fire in Harmony
这也行
That works too
灵珠天赋异禀
The Spirit Pearl has extraordinary abilities
岂能用常理判断
How can it be judged by ordinary standards?
你是师叔还是我是师叔
Are you the senior or am I?
你懂还是我懂
Do you understand or do I?
弟子不敢
This disciple dares not
但先前弟子似乎还感受到一股强大的魔气
But earlier, this disciple sensed a powerful demonic aura
哪里？当然是个石矶放出来的
Where? Of course, it came from Lady Stone
死胖子，你说什么
Fatty, what did you say?
老娘我分明.....是不是连宋
I, Lady Stone, clearly... is it Lian Song?
是不是你？是不是你？是不是你？
Was it you? Was it you? Was it you?
快说
Speak up
是我，是我
It was me, it was me
别摇动了
Stop shaking
要吐了
I'm about to hurl
你看！我说的吧
See! I told you
哪吒已连过三关
Nezha has passed three trials
今日老夫要亲自为你吟诵升仙咒
Today, I shall personally chant the Ascension Spell for you
遥想当年，我也经历过这些
Back in my day, I went through all this too
那时候可能太紧张了
I was probably too nervous back then
咋没觉得声升仙咒那么长呢
I don't remember the Ascension Spell being so long
从今往后
From now on
你便也是阐教仙人了
You shall be a Sage of the Orthodox Teachings
这玉虚宝库中珍藏的样样都是稀世法宝
The treasures in this Jade Void Treasury are all rare magical artifacts
玉液琼浆
Elixir and ambrosia
只能选一样
You can only choose one
你不多考虑考虑穷乡
Don't you want to think about the poor village
玉虚宫已派出信使
The Jade Void Palace has dispatched messengers
向12金仙通报龙族罪状
To inform the Twelve Golden Immortals of the Dragon Clan's crimes
但山高路远
But the mountains are high and the roads are long
仓促间种植地难以赶来
It's hard for them to arrive in a hurry
此次，老夫要亲率捕妖队讨伐龙族
This time, I will personally lead the monster-hunting team to punish the Dragon Clan
你愿与老夫一同出征否
Will you join me on this expedition
我先回陈塘关一趟
I'll go back to Chentang Pass first
然后就去找龙王算账
Then I'll go settle the score with the Dragon King
你战力非凡
Your combat skills are extraordinary
定可助老夫荡平龙宫
You can surely help me clear out the Dragon Palace
都还清了
It's all paid off
你等等，等我身体恢复
Wait, wait until I recover
我们一起去龙宫好不好
Let's go to the Dragon Palace together, okay
你知道我会做什么
You know what I can do
你去了，这只会更难受
If you go, it will only make things worse
下次见你
See you next time
是敌非友
Not a friend, but a foe
冤孽啊
What a curse!
你走不得，走不得
You can't leave, you can't leave
还没到龙宫你魂魄都消散了
Your spirit will be gone before you reach the Dragon Palace
你冷静一下好不好嘛
Can you please calm down?
你现在去了也改变不了任何事情啊
Going there now won't change anything
你别管我
Leave me alone
放我出去。一定要把你救活
Let me out. I must save you
憋死我了
I'm suffocating
何方神圣
Who are you?
老夫乃阐教无量仙翁
I am the Immortal Elder of the Orthodox School
敖光，你可知罪
Ao Guang, do you know your crimes?
你们都知道了
You all know
敖丙还活着吗
Is Ao Bing still alive?
我任由你们处置
Do with me as you will
能否放我儿子一条生路
Can you spare my son's life?
不知所谓
Nonsense
天庭令你龙族镇压海底妖兽
Heaven ordered your dragon clan to suppress the sea monsters
你们却勾结妖兽
But you conspired with the monsters
屠戮陈塘关
And slaughtered the people of Chentang Pass
陈塘关？龙族犯下滔天罪行
Chentang Pass? The dragon clan committed heinous crimes
今日老夫要替天行道啊
Today, I shall enforce the will of Heaven
保罗天地无量神通
Possessing boundless divine powers
天元现世，傲视群雄。打开
The primordial force emerges, towering over all. Open it
给我出来
Come out
你们对陈塘关干了什么
What have you done to Chentang Pass?
大哥不是叫我等听申道长的吩咐吗
Didn't the elder brother tell us to wait for Commander Shen's orders?
申公报
Shen Gongbao
火烧眉毛
It's an emergency
大哥还是先顾眼前吧
Elder brother, deal with the immediate problem first
大王不能坐以待毙啊
King, we can't just sit here and wait to die
我若出战
If I fight
这锁妖阵
This Demon Locking Array
锁妖阵交给我们吧
We'll handle the Demon Locking Array
拼尽全力，我们一炷香还是撑得了的
We can hold it for at least an incense stick's time
欺人太甚
This is an outrage
妖孽大胆
You dare to defy us
我们报仇雪恨的千载良机到了
Our chance for revenge has finally come
杀出炼狱荡清龙宫
We'll break out of this hell and cleanse the Dragon Palace
人刀合一
Become one with the blade
老鬼，看刀
Old ghost, taste my blade
这样释放魔气
Releasing this demonic energy
你小子不怕暴露身份吗
Aren't you afraid of exposing yourself?
我说过你要是敢动陈塘关
I told you, if you dare touch Chen Tang Pass
我就把龙宫砸个稀巴烂啊
I'll smash the Dragon Palace to pieces
说，熬丙是不是死了？
Tell me, is Ao Bing dead?
你不想活了
You want to die
看你肉身撑得了多久
Let's see how long your mortal body can last
我活不活无所谓
I don't care if I live or die
我只要你死
I just want you dead
机不可失
Don't miss this chance
看你们干的蠢事
Look at the mess you've made
难道同归于尽
Is mutual destruction
就是你们想要的结果
What you really want?
锁链
Chains
东海龙王竟也不是你对手
Even the Dragon King of the East Sea is no match for you
老夫果然没有看错
I haven't misjudged you
阐教就需要你这样的栋梁之材
The Daoist School of Complete Perfection needs a pillar of strength like you
你父母一生嫉恶如仇仇
Your parents were always righteous and hated evil
今后你也要继承他们的遗志
From now on, you must carry on their legacy
斩尽天下妖孽
and rid the world of all evil
老夫这就替你主持公道
I'll see justice done for you
炼化了这帮畜生
and purify these beasts
替我护法
Guard me while I do this
哪吒宝贝，宝贝，宝贝
My precious Nezha, my baby, my little one
爹，娘
Dad, Mom
儿啊，你没事吧
My child, are you alright?
你的肉身
Your mortal body
我..我..我..
I.. I.. I..
他们其实已经知晓你和敖丙的身份
They already know about you and Ao Bing
我..我
I.. I
我以为孩子见不到你们了
I thought the child would never see you again
师父还在施法
Master is still casting the spell
能拖一会儿是一会儿吗
We need to buy as much time as we can
哪吒，灭陈塘关的不是我父王
Nezha, it's not my father who destroyed Chentang Pass
真凶就是这无量仙翁
The real culprit is this Wuliang Immortal
结界兽
Boundary Beast
龙族~大师兄
Dragon Clan~ Senior Brother
别来无恙
Long time no see
你怎么在这
What are you doing here?
申公豹
Shen Gongbao
你勾结龙族意欲何为
Why are you colluding with the Dragon Clan?
我倒要问问问你
I want to ask you something
你抓我爹意欲何为
Why did you kidnap my father?
谁说我抓了你爹
Who said I kidnapped your father?
我家情况只有你清楚
Only you know our family's situation
若非你同意
If you hadn't agreed
哪吒和补妖队怎会找上我爹
Nezha and the Demon Hunters wouldn't have targeted my father
而且我弟的箭伤
And my brother's arrow wound
一看就知道是你徒儿鹿童所为
clearly shows it was your disciple, Lutong
不愧是老夫引荐入门的人才
You truly are the talented one I recommended
什么都逃不过你的眼睛
Nothing escapes your eyes
毕竟替你干过那么多年脏活儿
After all, I've done so many dirty jobs for you
我还能猜到你来陈塘关装神弄鬼的目的
I can guess why you're here in Chentang Pass, pretending to be a deity
你是想..嫁祸龙族
You're trying to frame the Dragon Clan?
你就是这样报答大师兄的栽培
Is this how you repay Master's kindness?
你一直把把我当工具
You've always treated me like a tool.
你与我之间有怨无恩
There's only resentment between us, no gratitude.
有兴趣做个交易吗
Interested in a deal?
仙长
Master.
你贵为玉虚宫的主事
As the head of Jade Void Temple,
想必知道解开这定海锁链的法咒
you must know the spell to unlock the Sea-Stabilizing Chains.
知道又怎样
So what if I do?
你你们要叛变
You're planning a rebellion?
千年前四弟兄一起对抗仙界
A thousand years ago, the four brothers fought against the celestial realm.
到底是谁先背信弃
Who was the first to break the trust?
将我们打入炼狱
Who cast us into the inferno?
无量仙翁要对付敖光
Wu Liang wants to take down Ao Guang.
我们求之不得
We couldn't be happier.
久闻无量仙翁用人不拘一格
I've heard Wu Liang is not one to be picky about his allies.
我等三哥的实力想必你也了解
I'm sure you're aware of our Third Brother's strength.
若能解救我等脱离炼狱，得道成仙
If you can free us from the inferno and grant us immortality,
我等甘愿为仆为奴
we will serve you loyally.
另外奉上灵珠和魔丸的秘密
And we'll share the secrets of the Spirit Pearl and the Demon Pill.
灵珠和魔丸
The Spirit Pearl and the Demon Pill.
卑鄙无耻。你们反抗..反抗仙界的傲骨呢？
How despicable. What happened to your defiance against the celestial realm?
以前年少无知
We were young and foolish back then.
经过千年牢狱
After a thousand years in prison,
才明白这世间的规则是由谁定
we've learned who sets the rules of this world.
聪明
Clever.
但你们反复无常
But you're fickle.
我怎信得过
How can I trust you?
除非让老夫在你们身上，我等愿意
Unless you place a curse on us, we are willing.
三个龙王自愿接受
The three Dragon Kings will accept it voluntarily.
无量仙王在他们身上下咒
Wu Liang will place a curse on them.
今后若敢抗命
If they ever disobey,
无量仙王随时可取他们性命
Wu Liang can end their lives at any time.
而无量仙翁则履行承诺
And Wu Liang will keep his promise.
解开了他们身上的定海锁链
He will release them from the Sea-Stabilizing Chains.
一旦发现强大实力
Once they detect great power,
便制造惨案
they stage a massacre.
栽赃陷害再派兵抓捕
They frame the culprit and send troops to arrest them.
据申公豹所说
According to Shen Gongbao,
他曾替无量仙翁干过不少这等勾当
he's done plenty of such dirty work
才换你们加入阐教的机会
to earn your chance to join the Orthodox Order.
此次无量仙翁本是为屠灭陈塘关
This time, Immortal Wu Liang was set to wipe out Chen Tang Pass,
栽赃东海龙族而来
framing the Eastern Sea Dragon Clan.
哪知却阴差阳错收编了三大龙王
But by a twist of fate, he ended up recruiting the three Dragon Kings,
并从他们口中获悉了魔丸和灵珠的秘密
and learned the secrets of the Demon Pill and the Spirit Pearl from them.
事后他们故意留下两个不明真相的活口
Afterward, they deliberately left two survivors in the dark,
放回玉虚宫通风报信
to return to Jade Void Palace and spread the news.
眼看突围无望
Seeing no way out,
申公豹想出一计
Shen Gongbao came up with a plan.
让夜叉先将我俩石化
He had the Night Forks turn us to stone,
再潜入下水道躲藏起来
then hide us in the sewers.
之后静待时机将我二人救活
Then, they would wait for the right moment to bring us back to life.
那你呢
What about you?
家人已逝
My family is gone.
我没什么好留恋的了
I have nothing left to hold on to.
补妖队捉去的妖
The monsters captured by the Demon Hunt Squad
并非如外界传言
aren't being reformed in Jade Void Palace,
在玉虚宫接受正道感化
as the rumors suggest.
而是都被无量仙翁投入
Instead, Immortal Wu Liang throws them into
这天元鼎炼成了仙丹
the Celestial Cauldron to be refined into elixirs,
提升阐教实力
boosting the Orthodox Order's power.
师兄啊
Brother!
你咋可能犯下这等罪行
How could you commit such a crime?
你你咋个对得起师尊对我们的教诲吗
How can you face the teachings of our Master?
现在你们既已知晓无量仙翁的罪行
Now that you know of Elder Immortal's misdeeds,
就因悬崖勒马将他押解回宫
we must rein him in and escort him back to the palace.
等待天尊降罪
To await the Celestial Lord's judgment.
捕妖队由无量仙翁亲手栽培
The monster-hunting squad was nurtured by Elder Immortal himself.
岂能三言两语就被你们策反啊
How could we be swayed by a few words?
是我错怪了龙族
I wronged the Dragon Clan.
放了龙族
Release the Dragon Clan.
我来帮你
I'll help you.
你们叛变！！跟大哥您学的
You traitors! Just like your big bro!
当初为了保全整个龙族，我没得选
To protect the entire Dragon Clan, I had no choice.
那现在为了保全自己
And now, to protect myself,
我也没得选
I have no choice either.
大王，等等我们，别丢下我们啊！大王
Your Majesty, wait for us! Don't abandon us! Your Majesty!
大王，带上我们
Your Majesty, take us with you!
你们都被卖了
You've all been sold out.
南海龙王
Southern Sea Dragon King
西海龙王
Western Sea Dragon King
侄儿，二叔陪你玩玩
Nephew, let's play a little.
捅死你
I'll skewer you!
老子劈死你
I'll chop you to bits!
小爷弄死你
I'll finish you off!
弄死你丫的
I'll do you in!
诶呦
Ow!
喂饱你了吗
Are you full now?
别乱说，哪里那么多
Don't be silly, there aren't that many.
你肉身不稳，别用力过度哦
Your physical form is unstable, don't overexert yourself.
我犯的错，哪怕死
For the mistakes I've made, even if it means death,
我也要帮你把龙族救出来
I have to help you save the Dragon Clan.
后生可畏啊
The young ones are formidable.
姑姑也来凑凑热闹
Auntie's here to join the fun.
你大欺小，耍赖
You're bullying the little one, that's cheating!
哎呀，你敢打你的师叔？
Oh no, you dare hit your uncle?
小的欺负大的。没文化
The little one's bullying the big one. How uncultured.
不行了，太乱了
This is getting out of control.
那就再乱些
Then let's make it even more chaotic.
来些水汽咋样，好
How about some mist? Sounds good.
小心两个小子偷袭
Watch out for those two sneaking up.
原来在这儿
There you are.
看着点，是我，二哥
It's me, your second brother.
对不住对不住
Sorry, sorry.
惊不惊喜？
Surprised?
变身术？
Transformation magic?
你疯了，你骗不了我
You're crazy! You can't fool me.
你们到底？暗号红凤凰黄凤凰
What's going on? The password is Red Phoenix, Yellow Phoenix.
啥？说不出暗号。假的
What? Can't say the password. Fake.
哼哼哼
Hehehe
原来你真是冒牌货
So you really are an impostor.
呸，活该
Pah, serves you right.
嗯？暗号？
Huh? The password?
呃，那个那个....
Uh, that, that...
防风防防横防错
Prevent, prevent, prevent mistakes.
哎呀
Oops.
是红凤凰
It's the Red Phoenix
黄凤凰
The Yellow Phoenix
粉红房上飞凤凰
The Pink House with the Flying Phoenix
我是真的呀
I'm telling the truth!
为什么这暗号我不会啊
Why don't I know this code?
我们刚编造的啊
We just made it up!
就不能编造的简单些吗
Couldn't we have made it simpler?
太难了
It's too hard!
你白痴啊
You fool!
别过来你个冒牌货
Stay back, you fake!
我是真的！
I'm real!
你放屁~你不知道暗号
You're lying! You don't know the code!
你还不会的
You don't know it either!
对啊
That's right!
难道我也是假的
Could I be a fake too?
我的天呐
Oh my gosh!
（咒语）太极天人五行睡醒
(Spell) Rise, Celestial Elements, Five Phases Awaken
三昧真火炼就金丹
True Fire Forges the Golden Elixir
急急如律令
As Ordered, Swiftly!
怕个毛啊
What's there to be afraid of?
用岩浆泡澡咱是家常便饭
Bathing in lava is just part of my routine!
哎呀，烫烫烫烫烫烫烫烫烫
Ouch, it's burning!
妈呀，是三昧真火
Good grief, it's the Three Pure Fires!
看什么呢
What are you looking at?
要吃也只能我自己吃
If anyone's eating, it'll be me!
美味的
Delicious
放了我父王
Release my father!
定住
Hold it!
好个灵珠也和魔丸般惊才绝艳
Well, the Spirit Pearl is just as brilliant as the Demon Pill!
穿心咒~！竟然早已知晓你们真实身份
Heart-Piercing Spell! You knew our true identities all along!
老夫岂能不留后手
I had to have a backup plan.
这不可能，不可能！
No way, this can't be!
这个咒语很复杂的
That spell is really complicated.
你啥时候下的咒语啊？
When did you cast the spell?
我说你年那个升仙咒怎么那么长时间
I wondered why the Immortal Ascension Spell took so long.
你夹带私货
You snuck something extra in there.
老匹夫
Old rascal!
即便魔丸三个时辰内
Even within three hours,
也休想冲破这穿心咒
the Demon Pill can't break through the Heart-Piercing Spell.
千针万刺已穿透全身经脉
A thousand needles and a myriad of thorns have pierced every meridian.
若强行活动
If he moves,
只会千刀万剐、四分五裂
he'll be torn to shreds.
难怪彼时老夫察觉不到活人气息
No wonder I couldn't sense any life force back then.
原来石化了
You were petrified.
但你们没死可就害了哪吒
But you being alive has doomed Nezha.
灵珠
Spirit Pearl,
魔丸都是宝啊
Demon Pill—both treasures!
老夫本想好好栽培栽培
I was planning to nurture you,
现在只能拿来炼丹了
but now I can only use you to make elixirs.
敖丙
Ao Bing,
父王，你你还活着
Father, you're alive!
无量仙翁下的穿心咒
The Heart-Piercing Spell by the Boundless Immortal.
栽到龙族的也是他
The Dragon Clan was also betrayed by him.
哪吒已经受了蒙骗不怪他
Nezha has been misled, so it's not his fault.
你想怎样都冲我来
If you have any issues, take them up with me.
和我爹娘无关
Leave my parents out of this.
杀了你们隐于事无补
Killing you won't change a thing.
大家都已难逃一死
We're all doomed anyway.
若还有放不下的恩怨
If there's any unfinished business,
自便吧
go ahead and settle it.
大师兄啊
Master Brother,
阐教乃名门正派
the Way of Enlightenment is a noble path.
你怎么能做出这等伤天害理之事呢
How could you commit such atrocities?
你莫要一错再错
Don't make things worse for yourself.
回去跟师傅认个错不好吗
Why not go back and apologize to the master?
我替你求情啊
I'll speak up for you.
你！敌我不分的蠢货
You! A foolish fool who can't tell friend from foe!
要是仙家地位稳如磐石
If the immortals' status were unshakable,
要是你们这帮养尊处优的小辈
if you pampered youngsters
有妖族一半努力
worked half as hard as the demon clans,
还用得着我费这劲
would I need to go through all this?
哪怕我粉身碎骨
Even if I am crushed to pieces,
背负骂名
and bear the blame,
一切都是为了阐教霸业永恒
it's all for the eternal glory of the Way of Enlightenment.
我
I
我问心无愧
I have a clear conscience.
呃，又烤好了一条
Uh, another one's done.
我是吃不下了
I can't eat any more.
你要不来点儿
Want to try some?
谢谢啊
Thanks.
等我的鱼翅烤熟了，你也尝尝
When my fish fins are ready, you can try them too.
蟹钳也烤好了
The crab claws are done too.
大家换着吃吧
Let's share and enjoy.
怎么回事啊
What's going on?
身
My
我我我我我,我的身体啊
My, my, my, my, my body!
被炼化成丹药了啊
Turned into a pill, huh?
我还年轻，我不想死了
I'm young, I don't want to die!
冷静！调动全部功力护体
Stay calm! Gather all your power to protect yourself!
能拖多久是多久
Hold on as long as you can.
儿啊，你功力强过我
Son, your power is greater than mine.
定能撑得更久
You can hold on longer.
若能撑到穿心咒失效
If you can outlast the Heart Piercing Curse,
就有逃生机会
there's a chance to escape.
这穿心咒至少三个时辰才能破除
The Heart Piercing Curse takes at least three hours to wear off.
我担心
I'm worried
撑不了那么久
we can't hold on that long.
夫人，娘，醒醒啊
Lady, Mother, wake up!
娘！宝贝
Mother! Darling!
宝贝！娘，我在这儿
Darling! Mother, I'm here!
你和爹都坚持住啊
Hold on, both of you!
不用管我们
Don't worry about us.
你自己守住心神
Focus on protecting yourself.
我还好，娘，我对这种火没感觉
I'm fine, Mother. This fire doesn't affect me.
你小子命大呀
You've got a lucky charm, kid.
若本王没猜错的话
If I'm not mistaken,
魔丸的魔焰和这三昧真火同宗同源
the demon flame from the demon pill and this Three Pure Fires share the same origin.
那这天云鼎就奈何不了你
So this Celestial Cauldron can't harm you.
不错
Exactly.
是老夫疏忽了
I underestimated you.
没用
It's useless.
这是我的化身而已
This is just my avatar.
哼哼，不愧是魔丸
Hmph, no wonder you're the demon pill.
坚不可摧
Indestructible.
难怪天尊要大费周章引天劫灭你
No wonder the Celestial Deity went to great lengths to summon the heavenly calamity to destroy you.
哈哈哈哈哈哈
Hahahaha
哪吒呀
Nezha,
老夫看你是个孝子
I see you're a filial son.
不如给你一个尽孝的机会
How about I give you a chance to show your filial piety?
灭魂丹
The Soul-Extinguishing Pill.
你若吞了它
If you swallow it,
老夫便放了你父母。如何？
I will spare your parents. What do you say?
老夫虽做事冷酷
Though I may seem cold,
但向来信守承诺
But I always keep my promises
不然也不会有那么多妖族能人异士效忠老夫
That's why so many talented demons are loyal to me
只要你吞了它
As long as you swallow it
老夫对天发誓
I swear to the heavens
绝不为难你父母
I won't harm your parents
要用他父母的命
Threatening the child with their parents' lives
要挟孩子自杀
To force the child to take their own life
你算神仙吗
Are you some kind of god?
你连做人都不配
You don't even deserve to be human
宝贝不要管我们
Darling, don't worry about us
你一定要活下去
You must stay alive
撑到穿心咒解开
Until the Heart-Piercing Curse is broken
撑到两个哥哥找到你
Until your two brothers find you
真以为老夫奈何不了魔丸
Do you really think I can't deal with the Demon Pill?
只是多费些功夫罢了
It just takes a bit more effort
等你们死了
Once you're dead
我有100种方法整死他
I have a hundred ways to finish him off
我只想最后死的有点的价值
I just want to die with some dignity
你们为什么不让我死
Why won't you let me die?
为什么不让我死
如果用你的命换爹娘
If your life could save your parents
你以为爹娘会心安理得的活下去吗
Do you think they would live on guilt-free?
宝贝，不，娘
Darling, no, Mom
娘会罩着你
Mom will protect you
不要紧
It's okay
最后
In the end
娘只想再抱抱你
Mom just wants to hold you one last time
娘不能陪你长大了
Mom can't be there to see you grow up
今后的路
The road ahead
你要自己走
You must walk it alone
我不，我没用，我没用
No, I'm useless, I'm useless
我们生来就是魔
We were born as demons
我一直让你们受苦
I've always made you suffer
我也要想成为
I want to be
成为你们的骄傲
the pride of you all
是我连累了你们
I've dragged you down
对不起，娘
I'm sorry, Mother
对不起
I'm sorry
和你度过的每一天，我都很开心
Every day with you was happy
我从没在乎你是仙还是魔？
I never cared if you were a god or a demon
娘只知道
Mother only knows
你是娘的儿子
You are Mother's son
娘永远爱...
Mother will always love...
宝贝不要冲动
Darling, don't be rash
停止，你骨肉会被撕裂的
Stop, or your flesh will tear apart
三昧真火竟然补全了重塑肉身时不足的温度
The Three Pure Fires have replenished the temperature needed for the reshaping of the flesh
哪吒的肉身
Nezha's physical form
完成了
is complete
照顾好娘
Take care of Mother
帮助我破开这鼎
Help me break this cauldron
不好，他们在吸收天元鼎的能量
No good, they're absorbing the energy from the Heavenly Cauldron
根深蒂固
Deep-rooted
全体补妖队听令，上
All demon hunters, attack!
父王，你们得留着功力护体啊
Father, you need to conserve your energy
我们一直在退避，一直在退避
We've been retreating, always retreating
原以为什么都给了
I thought giving everything
仙翁会让我们活下去
the Immortal would let us live
结果他们还要我们的命
But they still want our lives
既然他们要我们的命
Since they want our lives
那我们就用这条命跟他们拼了
We'll fight them with everything we've got
对。跟他们拼了，杀
Right. Fight them, kill
绝不能放他们出来
We can't let them out
不要放弃！坚持住
Don't give up! Hold on
给我破~~~~~~~~~~
Break it open~~~~~~~~~~
我的鼎好惨啊
My cauldron is so sad
阐教的根基啊
The foundation of the Chan School
给我杀光这帮畜生啊
Kill them all, you beasts!
你们这帮为虎作伥的小辈都黑白不分
You young pups can't tell right from wrong!
海啸龙吟
Tsunami Dragon Roar
原来仙翁手下竟也是俩禽兽
So even the sage's minions are monsters!
什么妖什么仙
What demons, what sages,
都是你们糊弄人的把戏
it's all just your trickery!
下贱的妖孽竟敢和我作对
You lowly demon, how dare you defy me!
见识下老夫的手段
See the power of an elder!
老夫惜才
I value talent,
再给你二人一次机会
and I'll give you one more chance.
若肯归降，保你们得道成仙
Surrender, and I'll ensure your ascension.
去你大爷的~小爷是魔那又如何
Go to hell! I'm a demon, so what?
自诩照世明灯
Claiming to be a beacon of light,
干的却是恃强凌弱
yet you bully the weak.
祸乱人间的勾当
You're the ones wreaking havoc in the world.
你们才是邪魔外道
You're the real devils!
无知小儿仙家雄霸天下
Ignorant brats, the sages rule the world,
依附强者才是唯一出路
and leaning on the strong is your only path.
否则天地虽大
Otherwise, though the world is vast,
也让你们无路可走
you'll find no place to stand.
若前方无路
If there's no way forward,
我就踏出一条路
I'll forge my own path.
若天地不容
If the world won't have me
我将扭转这乾坤
I'll turn it upside down
我的脸，我的脸
My face, my face
你们胆敢破坏的我功法
How dare you ruin my technique
我的不老神功
My eternal youth technique
回，回，回宫
Back, back, back to the palace
等等我
Wait for me
父王打算带领龙族前往大海深处隐匿起来
Your Majesty plans to lead the dragon clan to hide deep in the sea
你身份也已暴露
Your identity has been exposed
不如随我们一同去吧
Why don't you come with us
不了
No, thanks
以前我一直在躲在藏
I used to always hide
直到无路可走
Until I had nowhere to go
我才明白该如何面对这个世界
That's when I learned how to face the world
无量仙翁位高权重
Immortal Weng holds great power
又深得天尊信任
And has the trust of the Celestial Emperor
未必就会倒台
He might not fall from grace
而且仙魔殊途，水火不容
Besides, immortals and demons are like oil and water
什么神仙妖魔
What are these immortals and demons
不过是他们禁锢异族命运的枷锁
They're just chains that bind the fate of other races
哼，那又怎样
Humph, so what
难道你还想改变这世界
Do you still want to change the world
我想试试
I want to try
可能是我老了没力气再去和这个世界碰撞
Maybe I'm just too old to clash with the world anymore
父王知道
Your Majesty knows
一旦决定了事
Once you make a decision
你始终会去做
You always follow through
儿啊
My son
以前，父王让你肩负了太多的期望
In the past, I placed too many hopes on you
却不曾倾听你的想法
But I never listened to your thoughts
父王对不起你
Father, I've wronged you
父王只是想用自己的经验为你谋个幸福
Father just wanted to use his experience to secure your happiness
但现在看来
But now it seems
父辈的经验毕竟是过往
A father's wisdom is rooted in the past
未必全对呀
And not always right
你的路还需你去闯
Your path is one you must forge yourself
今后
From now on
忠于自己内心的选择吧
Follow the choices of your heart
我知道你会回来的
I know you'll come back
为什么
Why?
因为我们都太年轻
Because we're all too young
不知天高地厚
And don't know our limits
师傅，您的脸？不要紧
Master, your face? It's fine
鹤童给老夫敷过药了
Crane Boy has already applied the medicine
鼎被毁了，阐教已无必胜把握
With the cauldron destroyed, the Sect of Explanation has lost its edge
我们可是犯了弥天大罪呀
We've committed a grave sin
务必赶在师尊出关前马上行动
We must act before Master emerges from seclusion
我们走，去见见他
Let's go, we need to see him
关押的地方够隐秘吗
Is the place secure enough?
不会有其他人到这里来
No one else will come here
牢房内还屏蔽了仙术
The cell also blocks magical powers
大门也只有您和唯一一个守卫才开得了
Only you and one guard can open the door
开小差打瞌睡
Daydreaming and dozing off
怎么回事
What's going on?
这门认容貌
The door recognizes faces
您容貌有变
Your appearance has changed
需重新录入
It needs to be updated
敢嘲笑老夫？诅咒你睡10年
Dare to mock me? I curse you to sleep for 10 years
受罪了，师弟
You've suffered, little brother
师兄才是受罪
Big brother is the one who's suffered
谁把...把您打成这样
Who did this to you?
你可知老夫当年为何要引荐你入教
Do you know why I recommended you to the sect back then?
要的就是你这妖族身份
It was because of your demon heritage.
封神大战时
During the Great War of the Gods,
老夫可会对你委以重任
I could give you a crucial mission.
妄想
Dream on!
爹，爹
Dad, Dad!
还有呼吸
He's still breathing.
若你让老夫在你身上下个咒
If you let me place a curse on you,
你爹便可在玉虚宫尽享清福
your father can live out his days in peace at the Jade Void Palace.
您要的那两个人到了
The two people you asked for have arrived.
好好考虑考虑吧
Think it over carefully.
先前敷的药起效了
The medicine I applied earlier is working.
那怎么办
What do we do now?
还有谁能开门
Who else can open the door?
10年
10 years
五龙山云霄洞金吒，九宫山白鹤洞木吒
Jinzha from the Cloudy Cavern on Five-Dragon Mountain, and Muzha from the White Crane Cavern on Nine-Palace Mountain
应召回宫
have been summoned back to the palace.
师傅忍着点啊
Bear with it, Master.
差不多了吧？
Is it about right?
好像左眼还不够肿
The left eye doesn't seem swollen enough yet.
右腮也不补点
And the right cheek needs a bit more.
你们刚才是不是在笑
Were you guys laughing just now?
徒儿岂敢。师傅受苦
How could I, Master? I'm suffering.
徒儿心中只会难受百倍
I'm a hundred times more distressed.
真的绝无虚言
Truly, not a word of a lie.
天地可鉴
Heaven and earth can bear witness.
行了，哎呀，行了行了
Alright, oh, alright, alright.
这回快点吧
Hurry up this time.
好像打多了
Looks like we hit too many times.
没事啊，没事没事，敷伤药
It's fine, it's fine, just apply the medicine.
一会儿好了再来啊
We'll come back once it's healed.
师傅，你是干大事的人
Master, you're a great man.
你这都是为了阐教兴亡
All this is for the prosperity of the sect.
我们多尝试几次，总会打开这门的
We'll try a few more times; we'll get this door open.
抓住他，别让他跑了，快上药
Hold him, don't let him run, quick, apply the medicine.
放开我，放开我啊啊
Let me go, let me go!